<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Infants faith, and right to baptism, proved from Scripture with the chief objections against it answered. By John Hunt, pastor of a particular congregation in Northampton.</title>
            <author>Hunt, John, fl. 1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3739A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221348</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37142</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2148:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Infants faith, and right to baptism, proved from Scripture with the chief objections against it answered. By John Hunt, pastor of a particular congregation in Northampton.</title>
                  <author>Hunt, John, fl. 1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R. Janeway, and sold by the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Infants Faith,</hi> AND RIGHT TO BAPTISM, Proved from
Scripture; WITH THE Chief Objections againſt it Anſwered.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Hunt,</hi> Paſtor of a Particular Congregation in
<hi>Northampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 8.20.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony: if they ſpeak not
according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no Light in them.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Joh. 5.34.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>I receive not Teſtimony from Man.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Tim. 4.3.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>For the time will come, when they will not endure ſound
Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Joh. 12.48.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>The word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall Judge him in
the laſt Day.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Janeway,</hi> and Sold by the
Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou mayeſt well wonder, that in this Day, when the World can
ſcarce contain the Books already Written, that this Little Piece ſhould
croud in among the reſt under my Hand: And more eſpecially, on ſuch a
Subject, as hath been ſo Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and Learnedly inſiſted on by ſo
many Worthy Servants of Christ; who have been daily bringing out of their
Treaſury concerning this Matter, contained in this Book, things New 
<pb facs="tcp:37142:3"/>and Old; and what can the Man ſay that cometh after the King? But
though it may ſeem ſtrange on this Account, yet I hope ſome Satisfactory
Reaſons may be produced why I have engaged in this Work.</p>
            <p>For ſince the Providence of God hath caſt my Lot at
<hi>Northampton,</hi> it hath no little concerned me, to ſee how Generally
the County is Infected, not only with Anabaptiſm, but alſo with thoſe
many and groſs Errors, which commonly that Doctrine is an inlet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and
eſpecially, with that Soul-dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Error of Free-Will: And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo,
but even ſome among my own Flock, over which the Holy Ghost hath made me
Overſeer, (though, Bleſſed be God, far enough from the Doctrine of
Free-Will) are diſſatisfied about Infants Right to Baptiſm: And for the
ſake of thoſe I have Printed this; not deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, if poſſible, to
be expoſed beyond the extent of my Church; and if it goes further, I would
have the Reader<pb facs="tcp:37142:3"/>look upon it as having ſtrayed beyond its
deſigned Bounds.</p>
            <p>And could no other Reaſon be given but this, I think it may
excuſe me; for ſince God hath ſet me a Watchman over this Flock, I think
my ſelf bound (as ever I hope to give up my Account with Joy) to take all the
Care of them I can, and to do my utmost to reduce ſuch as are wandering, and
to eſtabliſh ſuch as are wavering; and to keep the Plague out of their
Head, as well as their Hands, from being Defiled: Judging a Blind Eye, worſe
than a Lame Foot. Errors in Judgment are like to be an inlet into continual
Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Practice.</p>
            <p>And as ſome of my People ſtand in need of information in this
Point, ſo there are ſome that deſire to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; which is no ſmall
Motive to me to Write: And becauſe I love not to ſpend my time in my Pulpit
in Controverted Points, I have therefore expoſed my Sentiments to the meanest
Capacity that can but Read.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:37142:4"/>But beſides all this, I have been importunately
urged by ſeveral Friends, whom I highly eſteemed, to Print this, (having
ſeen the Copy) who hope it may be Serviceable to the Church of God in the
Neighbouring Parts; and though I love to live an obſcure Life, and never
could entertain one thought of appearing at ſo publick a Poſt; tho'
frequently, in other Caſes, urged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: Yet for theſe Reaſons, I
have been prevailed upon; and while I find my Mind ſo ſtrangely changed in
this reſpect, I would hope I have the Mind of God in it.</p>
            <p>READER, Though I have not ſtudied to pleaſe this wanton Age,
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never affected Novelties in Matters of Religion, but rather to ſtand
and enquire for the Good Old Way; and to Contend earneſtly for the Faith once
delivered to the Saints; Yet I doubt not but much of what is contained herein,
will ſeem new to most Vulgar Capacities. But as I judge it not ſafe to
embrace any thing becauſe<pb facs="tcp:37142:4"/>new, (as is the Cuſtom with many in
our Day) for thus we may be ever learning, and never able to come to the
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth: So on the other Hand, I judge it dangerous to reject
any Truth proved to be ſo from Scripture, becauſe it ſeems new, or above
our reach: But however ſtrange it may appear, I could have cited ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
worthy Authors of my Judgment; but I receive not my Teſtimony from Men.</p>
            <p>If therefore I have not proved what I have laid down from
Scripture, then reject it; but if I have, you are bound to receive it; and not
to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as mine; and must own, 'tis through your ignorance if it
ſeems ſtrange unto you.</p>
            <p>I have not ſtudied Eloquence in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of this; nay,
rather I have ſtudied to ſhun and avoid it, and to ſpeak in the
Demonſtration of the Spirit of God; comparing Spiritual things with
Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; that ſo the enſuing Diſcourſe might the better ſuite with
thoſe for<pb facs="tcp:37142:5"/>whom I deſigned it. I hope, <hi>Reader,</hi> thou wilt
find that I have managed this Diſcourſe with all Mildneſs and Moderation;
and have only put a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Conſtruction on thoſe many Texts I have cited;
and yet I cannot but fear this will enrage ſome Men, who are lovers of a
Party, more than lovers of Truth; who can eaſier cry up their own Opinions
than ſolidly confute other Arguments.</p>
            <p>As I did not intend in Writing this, to Enter the List with any in
a Publick. Debate, or to provoke any to make a Reply; ſo, if contrary to my
expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, any of the common Diſputants of our Age ſhall think good to
Anſwer it, I deſign to take no further notice of it, than to Read it; not
doubting but they will be found to oppoſe God as well as me, in the Judgment
of any who eſteem the Scripture as the Word of God, or prefer it above their
own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and that while they open their Mouths to oppoſe the Truth ſo
clearly proved; they will but belch out their<pb facs="tcp:37142:5"/>Arminian Tenets; and
as Raging Waves, foam out their own ſhame, and be as unſucceſsful in
their Attempts, as thoſe who never would ceaſe endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſet up
<hi>Dagon,</hi> in oppoſition to the Ark; till only the Stump remained. But
however this may inrage others, <hi>who know not what manner of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they
are of;</hi> yet if it may but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit my own Flock, I have gained my chief
Deſign. Which that it may, ſhall be the Earnest and Continual Prayer, of
him who bears a dear Love and Affection to their Souls; and who is willing to
ſerve the advancing the Interest of Christ in the meanest Place in his
Houſe;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Hunt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37142:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Infants FAITH</hi> AND RIGHT TO BAPTISM, Proved from
Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Conſideration of the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Differences, which are this
Day among the People of God, about the Doctrine of Infant Baptiſm; (whereby
God is much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and the Adverſaries Mouths opened, to reproach
the Ways and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God; whereby much time is ſpent in Controverſies,
which might be better improved in giving diligence <hi>To make our 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37142:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Calling and Election ſure;</hi> and in helping each
other forward in the way to Heaven; hath moved me to try, if by the
Bleſſing of God on my weak Endeavours, I might be that happy Inſtrument,
to put an end to that Controverſie: For it's pity ſuch as agree ſo in
Fundamentals, ſhould ſo much differ about Smaller Matters; and that they
who hold one Lord, and one Faith, ſhould not hold one and the ſame
Baptiſm all reſpects: And though enough hath been Delivered and Printed on
this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject by divers worthy Lights, to ſatisfie any impartial Reader, and
clear Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; yet becauſe many have not time to Read, or Money to
Buy, or Capacities to Underſtand large Volumes; I ſhall add this ſhort
Tract, as a Mite to the former Treaſury: In which I ſhall Study both
Brevity and Plainneſs of Speech; to tho End that, if poſſible, I might
not over-reach the meaneſt Capacity; ſince it is for the ſakes of ſuch,
I deſign this; and therefore to prevent tediouſneſs, I ſhall ſum up
all I ſhall ſay, as to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Baptiſm, in two Arguments more
generally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Argument in Defence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſm is
this; If we Gentiles do<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37142:7"/>come in the room of the Jews then we
muſt partake of their Priviledges; but we Gentiles do come in the Jews room,
therefore we muſt partake of their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. The Major I muſt take for
gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: For how, or to what end do we come in their room; unleſs we partake
of their External Church Priviledges? One of which was Circumciſion.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1,2. <hi>What advantage then hath the Jew? Or what Profit is
there of Circumciſion?</hi> Much every way, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Ordinance
was to be adminiſtred unto Infants of Eight Days Old; in the ſtead of which
God hath appointed the Ordinance of Baptiſm, as is clear from that plain
Text, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10,11,12. <hi>And ye are compleat in him, which is the
Head of all Principality and Power. In whom alſo ye are Circumciſed with
the Circumciſion made without Hands, in putting off the Body of the Sins of
the Fleſh, by the Circumciſion of Chriſt: Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him in
Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. In which place the Apoſtle is incouraging the
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Coloſſians</hi> to ſtand faſt in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to
thoſe falſe Teachers, who would Preach the Law as a Covenant of Works, or
at leaſt mixed Law and Goſpel together, in oppoſition to whom, he tells
them they<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37142:8"/>were compleat in him, that is, in Chriſt; and
however theſe falſe Teachers might pretend a neceſſity to keep the Law,
yet he here lets them know, foraſmuch as Chriſt was made under the Law, and
did bring in an everlaſting Righteouſneſs, and that he did in their room
and ſtead; hence they that believed were compleat in Chriſt their Head, and
ſo under no Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to keep the Law, as a Covenant of Works, Chriſt
being the End of the Law, (in that reſpect) to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth.</p>
            <p>But leſt thoſe falſe Teachers ſhould prevail to draw away
Diſciples after them, by urging the neceſſity of Circumciſion, he tells
them they were Circumciſed with the Circumciſion made without Hands, or had
received the End of Circumciſion; for that ſignified a neceſſity of the
Heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sanctified, <hi>Rom</hi> 2.28. which Grace of Sanctification, as
well as Juſtification, they received from Chriſt, and ſo were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat
in him; but that they ſhould not think themſelves inferiour to them for
want of the external Seal, he tells them they had the Seal of the Covenant
alſo; and though not the ſame, yet a milder in its room; <hi>Buried with
him in Baptiſm.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37142:8"/>Nor do I ſee what other deſign the
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle can have in theſe words, but to prove, that Baptiſm to us, comes
in the room of Circumſiſion to the Jews; and that you may ſee that this
is not my own private Sence of theſe Words, I ſhall cite another Witneſs
or two to confirm it. Of the ſame Judgment is the Learned <hi>Paraeus;</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>Quod Apoſtolus precedente verſu, de Externa &amp; Interna
Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one dixit ad Inſtitutionem &amp; Conſolationem fidelium,
contra pſeudo-Judees; eadem nunc applicat ad fideles in Novo Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
in quo Circumciſioni ſucceſſit Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Baptiſmi,</hi> i. e. That
which the Apoſtle had ſaid in the foregoing Verſe, concerning External
and Internal Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, for the Inſtruction and Conſolation of
Believers againſt the falſe Jews, he applies the ſame to Believers in the
New Teſtament, in which the Sacrament of Baptiſm doth ſucceed in the room
of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion: Of the ſame Judgment is <hi>Calvin, Aretius,</hi> and
many more; whoſe words for brevity ſake I ſhall omit, and come to my
Minor Propoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Minor.</hi> But we Gentiles do come in the Jews room; which I
prove from that plain Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.19,20,24. <hi>Thou wilt 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37142:9"/>ſay then, The Branches were broken off, that I might be
graffed in. Well: becauſe of Unbelief they were broken off, and thou
ſtandeſt by Faith, be not high-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but fear. For if thou wert cut out
of tho Olive Tree, which is wild by Nature, and wert graffed contrary to Nature
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Good Olive Tree,</hi> &amp;c. Now our Graffing in, muſt anſwer to
the Cutting off of the Jews; or elſe the Apoſtle miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of his Scope
and Deſign. Nor was their breaking off, a breaking off from a real Union with
Chriſt, as ſome of the Anabaptiſts have in my hearing affirmed, to avoid
the force of this Text; but from External Church Priviledges. Now, ſince the
Infant Seed of the Jews had a Right to Circumciſion; if then we Believing
Gentiles do come in their room, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm in the room of Circumciſion,
as I think I have ſufficiently proved (if Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture may determine the
Matter) then we and our Seed muſt have a Right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm under the New
Teſtament, as the Jews and their Seed had to Circumciſion under the Old
Teſtament: But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Scripture is ſo clear for this, yet
that no doubt may remain, I ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37142:9"/>ſuch
Objections as may poſſibly be made againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. If we come in the Jews room, then all the
Children in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought to be Baptized; ſince all the Children in the
Jewiſh Nation were Circumciſed: But according to your Practice all ought
not to be Baptized; therefore from your Practice we may Judge you do not think
we come in their room.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All that can be truly inferred from hence is
this, That as all in their Church, which was National, were to be
Circumciſed; ſo all in our Particular Churches ought to be Baptized; and
this is no more than I earneſtly contend for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. But if we come in their room, then we muſt
be a National Church, as they were, or elſe how can we be ſaid to partake
of their Priviledges?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was not of the Eſſence of the Jewiſh
Church, that it was National; nor was it any Priviledge above what it would
have been, had it been divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to particular Churches as we are. I grant,
that ſo long as the Temple ſtood, which was a Type of Chriſt, ſo long
God required they ſhould meet to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37142:10"/>him there;
which might ſerve to ſhew how the gathering of the People ſhould be unto
Chriſt: But now, though it was their Priviledge that they might Worſhip,
yet it muſt needs be burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to come from all Parts of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to
Worſhip at the Temple, and at ſuch expence: But now God hath eaſed us of
this burden, while he hath appointed Particular Churches, where we enjoy all
the Worſhip of God, with as great a Promiſe of the Preſence of God as
they had in the Temple, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.20. So that we only want (if I may
ſo ſay) the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of the Worſhip. God hath not now confined us
to Places; <hi>John.</hi> 4.20,21. <hi>The hour cometh when ye ſhall neither
in this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>Worſhip the Father;</hi>
that is, with reſpect to Places. And yet though we are not confined to their
Place of Worſhip, yet we are ſaid to be graffed into their Olive; and as
for ſuch as lay ſuch ſtreſs on this, as if it was impoſſible we
ſhould come in the Jews room, unleſs we were a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church, I would
ask them this Queſtion, Do you believe that the Jews ſhall in time be
brought home again, and Ingraffed into their own Olive, from which 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37142:10"/>they have been ſo long broken off? And further, Whether
you think at that Day, they ſhall Worſhip God in the Temple, and offer
Gifts and Sacrifices, as once they did? Now that they ſhall be reſtored and
brought home again, is clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12,15,26. <hi>Now if the
Fall of them be the Riches of the World, and the Diminiſhing of them the
Riches of the Gentiles; how much more their Fulneſs? For if the caſting
away of them be the Reconciling of the World: What ſhall the receiving of
them be, but Life from the Dead?</hi> From theſe and the following Verſes
it is moſt clear, that the Jews ſhall be one Day reſtored, and it is that
which we now are expecting; but that they ſhall then Worſhip at the Temple,
when it hath been demoliſhed ſo many hundred Years; and that they ſhall
offer Sacrifices, after they come to Believe that Chriſt the great Sacrifice
is offered, or that the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> ſhould only Miniſter before
the Lord, when all the Tribes have been ſo ſhattered and confuſed in this
Dark and Gloomy Day, all ſeem to me to be things incredible. Now if they
ſhall be graffed again into their own Olive (as the Scripture affirms)
notwithſtanding ſo<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37142:11"/>many, and ſo great alterations in
their VVorſhip, as we have good ground from Scripture to believe there will
be; VVhy may not we Gentiles be ſaid to come in their room, though we are not
confined to all the Circumſtances of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſince we want
nothing that was a Priviledge?</p>
            <p>And more eſpecially, if we conſider that we have good ground
to believe that their graffing in again, will be no more than to beſtow
thoſe very Priviledges on them, which we Gentiles do now enjoy; as ſeems
clear to me from <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.31. <hi>Even ſo have theſe alſo now not
believed; that through your Mercy, they alſo may obtain Mercy.</hi> Mind,
that through your Mercy, or the Mercy of God to you, they alſo may obtain
Mercy: As if he had ſaid, the conſideration of your Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or the
Priviledges which you enjoy under the Goſpel, ſhall be a means not only to
convince them that the Meſſiah is come, but ſhall alſo ſtir them up
to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ſame Faith, that ſo they may partake of the ſame Mercies
with you. So that it ſeems evident, not only from Scripture, but Reaſon it
ſelf; that when the Jews come to be Reſtored, it will on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37142:11"/>be to ſhare with us Gentiles in our Priviledges: And yet
this is called in Scripture, a graffing in again. So that there is no more
neceſſity for us to be confined to all the Circumſtances of their
VVorſhip, in order to our coming in their room; than for them to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
to all the Circumſtances of their wonted Service, when graffed in again: Nor
doth it ſeem credible, that when they are graffed in again, they ſhall
injoy nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumciſion, nor any other Seal in its room, and that their
Priviledges ſhould be leſs under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Diſpenſation,
than under the Old; that God ſhould own their Seed then, and reject them now.
Sure I am, this would in all probability, be a great Block in their way, to
prevent their embracing the Goſpel. Circumciſion was an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of high
eſteem with them, as we may judge by their chearful undergoing ſo much pain
and ſmart as it occaſioned; as we may gather from <hi>Ex.</hi> 4.26. <hi>A
Bloody Husband thou art, becauſe of the Circumciſion.</hi> But now, if we
can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them that we have a milder Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and Seal in its room, this
may have a great Influence upon them, by<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37142:12"/>tſie Bleffing of
God, in order to the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in.</p>
            <p>Thus I have finiſhed my firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſhould I add no
more in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Doctrine of Infant Baptiſm, it might ſuffice;
unleſs Perſons are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſhut their Eyes that they might not
behold the Light, ſince I have clearly proved from Scripture, that we
Gentiles do come in the Jews room, and Baptiſm in the room of Circumciſion:
But to the end there may not be left one Stone upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that Strong
Hold, which the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts have raiſed againſt this Truth, which may
not be thrown down, I ſhall raiſe one. Argument more as a Battery againſt
it, and ſhall add no more: And indeed I think I need add no more, being
ſatisfied theſe Arguments will be as a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Cord that will not eaſily
be broken. Now the great Objection of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, againſt Infant
Baptiſm, is founded on ſuch Scriptures as hold forth Faith as neceſſary
in order to Baptiſm; as <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that Believeth, and is
Baptized, ſhall be ſaved, Acts</hi> 8.37. <hi>And</hi> Philip <hi>ſaid,
if thou Believeſt with all thy Heart, thou mayeſt. Acts</hi> 18.8. <hi>And
many of the</hi> Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>hearing, Believed, and were Baptized.</hi> 
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37142:12"/>And from theſe, and ſuch like Texts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently
conclude, that becauſe none but Adult Perſons have or can have Faith,
therefore none but ſuch ought to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized: And if I miſtake not, here
lays the ſtreſs of all their Arguments.</p>
            <p>Now for the preventing any miſtake, (that none may ſuppoſe
the Difference to be wider than it is) if it be enquired ther ſome Adult may
not be Baptized; I grant they may; provided they never have been Baptized in
their Infancy; and yet this may rationally be Inferred from ſuch Texts; for
thoſe that Believed and were Baptized, had never before been Baptized, nor
had they made any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt before then, that we know of; the
Text ſeem to prove they were Baptized immediately upon their Confeſſion
of Faith; and ſhould I meet with ſuch, I ſhould think my ſelf bound
from ſuch Examples to Baptize them. So that we agree with the Anabaptiſts
in this, that ſome Adult ought to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. But the Grand Queſtion in
Debate is, whether ſome Infants ought not to be Baptized as well as Adult;
this the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts deny, and I affirm, and prove<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37142:13"/>thus,
from this following Argument; and it ſeems cogent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 2. Thoſe that the Scripture give us good
ground to hope are Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, may and ought to be Baptized; but the Infant
Seed of Believers are ſuch as we have good ground from Scripture to hope are
Believers; therefore ſuch may and ought to be Baptized. All that I can
conceive can be ſaid againſt my Major Propoſition is, to deny that we are
to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize any upon hopes that they are Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; and to affirm that we
ought to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize none but ſuch as we are ſure have true Juſtifying
Faith. But ſure I am ſuch an Objection ſavours of high Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption;
ſince this is to pretend to be Wiſer than the Apoſtles, and as Wiſe as
God himſelf. Firſt, Wiſer than the Bleſſed Apoſtles; as you may
ſee by comparing <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. with 22.23. where you read of one
Baptized <hi>that was in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and Bonds of Iniquity;</hi>
and yet we cannot be ſo uncharitable as to think they had no hopes of him
when they Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized him: But if any ſhould ſo judge, it makes the more for
me; for if the Apoſtles themſelves Baptized ſuch as they had no 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37142:13"/>hopes had true Faith; then ſure we may Baptize ſuch
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we have good ground to hope
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Faith: But if they had Hope,
'tis evident it was but Hope, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he could loſe his Faith, or have
Faith, and at the ſame time be in the Gall of Bitterneſs and Bonds of
Iniquity; neither of which could be. Secondly, This is to pretend to be as
wiſe as God (at leaſt in this point) ſince he only that works Faith can
infallibly judge where it is. 'Tis peculiar to God to ſearch the Heart, where
Faith is ſeated; the Lord only knows who are his; we ſee the beſt of
Churches have been miſtaken in taking in of Members. The Apoſtles did not
know <hi>Judas</hi> to be a Hypocrite, till he betrayed his Lord, (unleſs we
can ſuppoſe they would take in known Hypocrites). And I would ask my
Friends, the Anabaptiſts, if they themſelves have not Baptized ſome as
Believers, who have afterward diſcovered themſelves to be in the Gall of
Bitterneſs. So that (in a word) if we muſt Baptize none but ſuch as we
are ſure have true Juſtifying Faith, we muſt Baptize none in this World:
For though many have ſuch a Faith, yet no Man can infallibly tell (the
Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt themſelves not excepted) who they are.<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37142:14"/>This
is that new Name which none knows but God, and them that have it. So that I
think it needleſs to add any more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the former part of my Argument,
<hi>viz.</hi> That we can only hope that this or the other Perſon hath true
Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Minor Propoſition.</hi> But the Infant Seed of Believers are
ſuch, as we have good ground from Scripture to hope are Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. Now if
any thing of force be Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, it muſt be againſt this; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I
ſhall labour the more to confirm it: But before I come to the Proof, I muſt
add a Caution, that when I ſpeak of Faith in Infants, I mean Habitual Faith;
for though it cannot on good ground be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but that ſome Infants may
actually Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ſince God is able to cauſe them ſo to do, and hath no
where in his Word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared he will not; yet it may eaſily be proved, that
ſome Infants have Habitual Faith; and that will render one as truly a
Believer as the Act. He that hath the Habit of Faith, is a Believer, though
aſleep, and ſo as uncapable of Acting Faith as an Infant; having (during
that time) no more uſe of Reaſon than a Child at the Breaſt, nor perhaps
ſo much; for an Infant hath ſo much Senſe as to know<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37142:14"/>when it is Hungry, or to Cry for Food; and if it be in Pain. But let a
Man be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo Hungry, or in Pain; yet when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, he is unſenſible
of either: And yet ſuch may be Believers in the mean time, they having the
Habit of Faith. Now by the Habit of Faith in Infants, I mean a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of
Grace, or Internal Renovation which is wrought in Regeneration; for
Regeneration is an infuſing the Seeds of all Grace into the Soul, and
conſequently of Faith. This being premiſed, I come to lay down a
Propoſition for the clearing the Way to that which I intend more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to
inſiſt upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition.</hi> That Infants are capable of having the
Habit of Faith wrought in them: And though we cannot from hence conclude that
all ſuch have it, yet it is a good Foundation for my following Argument: And
becauſe in all Caſes the Foundation had need ſtand faſt, I ſhall
therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it; that Infants are capable of Grace, is not my Judgment
alone (however ſtrange a Doctrine it may ſeem to ſome) for I have the
Judgment of all the Church of <hi>England</hi> on my ſide; their Words af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Baptiſm are, <hi>Seeing now, Dearly beloved Brethren, that this Child is by
Baptiſm<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37142:15"/>Regenerate,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>We yield
thee moſt hearty thanks moſt merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it hath pleaſed thee
to Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate this Infant by thy Holy Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. Now though I am far
from being of the Judgment which they ſeem to be in this, that all that are
Baptized are in that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Regenerated, and ſo conſequently many fall
from Grace. My Soul abhorrs that Popiſh Doctrine, that Baptiſm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
Grace, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> from the Work-wrought; but while they thank
God for the Work done, 'tis evident they ſuppoſe them capable of having
that Work wrought in them; and ſo far I agree with them. But becauſe the
very citing any thing from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may make ſome
giddy-headed People (who have more Zeal than ſound Knowledge) nauſeate what
I have ſaid. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proceed to prove, that both they and I have
Divine Teſtimony on our ſide in this, that Infants are capable of Grace;
and I ſhall make uſe of plain Scripture, ſince the Anabaptiſts pretend
ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it; and I ſhall produce ſeveral Inſtances, that in
the Mouth of two or three Witneſſes, this truth may be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.
<hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Before thou cameſt out<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37142:15"/>of the Womb,
I Sanctified thee;</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> 1.15. of <hi>John</hi> it is ſaid,
<hi>He ſhall be filled with the Holy Ghoſt, even from his Mothers
Womb;</hi> and then no doubt Sanctified. And of Chriſt it is ſaid, verſe
35. <hi>That Holy Thing that ſhall be born of thee,</hi> &amp;c. mind, born
of thee, was Holy when Born: From whence it is paſt all diſpute, (unleſs
we dare diſpute with God) that Infants, even in the Womb, and as ſoon as
Born, are capable of Grace; nor doth it ſeem harder to me to conceive, that
Infants ſhould have Grace wrought in them than Adult, ſince the latter are
purely paſſive in the Work, and ſo may the former be. If it was a Work of
Reaſon, or performed by Humane Power or Policy, ſomething might be ſaid,
but it is not, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19. Nay, according to our apprehenſion, it
ſeems harder to work Grace in Adult than in Infants; for as a Tender Plant is
more eaſily eradicated than a Grown Tree, ſo in this Caſe, Sin by
Cuſtom and Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance gets root; and though all things are equally
poſſible to God, yet to change an Old Sinner is moſt difficult in it
ſelf. We may conceive a greater oppoſition in the Heart of Grown Perſons
to a Work of Grace than in Infants: The longer we<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37142:16"/>have been
wedded to Sin, the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing we ſhall be to give it a Bill of Divorce,
and put it away. So that Infants are as capable of Grace as Adult, and more
capable, as to the Humane Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any, unleſs Arminians. And though
'tis ſaid Faith comes by hearing, yet that only points out the ordinary way
of God's Working Faith in Adult. This directs us to our Duty, but ſets no
bounds or limits to his Power. God can work Faith other ways than by the
hearing of the Ear, if he will. Thus having cleared my Propoſition, that
Infants are capable of Faith, I now come to confirm the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Propoſition of
my Argument, which was this, That the Infant Seed of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are ſuch, as
we have good ground from Scripture to hope are Believers. Before, I proved
Infants were capable of Faith; now, I come to prove, ſome Infants have Faith;
which I prove thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument.</hi> If ſome Infants get to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, then ſome
Infants have Faith: But ſome Infants do get to Heaven, therefore ſome
Infants have Faith. 'Tis poſſible that the Anabapatiſts may ſay, That
there is no neceſſity for Infants to have Faith, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their getting
to Heaven; but I am<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37142:16"/>loth to reſign up ſuch a Goſpel
Truth, meerly becauſe they have ſaid it. I ſhall lay down nothing but
what I ſhall prove from plain Scripture, and I ſhall expect the ſame of
them; eſpecially in Matters of ſuch grand Import. And ſure I am the
Scripture no where affirms any ſuch thing, that any can get to Heaven without
Faith-Nay, Nay, I am certain, the whole Currant of Scripture doth, in moſt
expreſs terms, run directly contrary thereunto; as I ſhall ſhew anon. So
that we cannot open our Mouths in Defence of ſuch a Notion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we dare
even fight againſt God. I grant indeed, there are ſome Secrets in God's
working in Infants; yet this makes nothing againſt the Truth of the thing,
becauſe we cannot comprehend it. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive the manner how God works
Grace in Adult, unleſs very imperfectly, As, <hi>John</hi> 3.8. <hi>the Wind
Bloweth where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the Sound thereof; but canſt
not tell whence it cometh, nor whither it goeth; ſo is every one that is Born
of the Spirit.</hi> Mind, every one; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult as well as Infants; where Chriſt
himſelf makes it as hard, to know how God Regenerates, as to give Account of
the Wind, which hath puzzled our wiſeſt<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37142:17"/>Philoſophers:
We may feel the Wind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh us, and ſee the effects of it, but cannot
tell exactly how it is cauſed. So in this Caſe, we may find and feel the
refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Influence of the Spirit in our ſelves, and may ſee the
effects of it in others, yet can no more comprehend the manner of his working,
than we can conceive how the Body is formed in the Womb of her that is with
Child. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.5. There you have theſe two compared. Why then
ſhould it be thought incredible that God ſhould Work Faith in Infants?
Though we cannot fully comprehend his way of Working, God can make uſe of
various ways to effect one and the ſame thing, though in the mean time he
gives us no account of his Matters; <hi>His ways are in the deep Waters, and
his Footſteps are not known.</hi> And ſure I am, if we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
nothing but what we can fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, the Articles of our Faith may
ſtand in leſs room; for what can we ſay as to the Trinity; we are bound
to believe ſuch a thing becauſe God hath revealed it; but alas how little
can we comprehend, of Three in One, or to the Hypoſtatical Union of Two
Natures Perſonally united? What ſhall we ſay as to the Reſurrection 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37142:17"/>of the Dead? Of the Joys of Heaven, or the Torments of
Hell? If nothing muſt be Believed but what we can comprehend, we muſt blot
out theſe and many more Articles of our Creed. Is not this the way to
Atheiſm, if we muſt not believe God to be, unleſs we can comprehend him,
ſince 'tis but a little portion we have heard of him, <hi>Job.</hi> 26.14.
and ſince none can by ſearching find out God to Perfection? This is to
prefer the Light within, or Carnal Reaſon above the Word of God, if we muſt
not believe God's Word, unleſs we can comprehend it. Nay, this is to make a
Man worſe than a Beaſt, while he muſt not believe that which he ſees:
Hence we muſt not believe ſuch a thing as the Tide or Sun; ſince though
it is eaſie to ſee both, yet we cannot fully comprehend either. Nay, at
this rate, we muſt not believe our ſelves to be Creatures, ſince we
cannot tell how we were formed in the dark Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the Womb; for we
are ſaid to be wonderfully made. In a word, by this Rule we muſt believe
nothing, becauſe there is nothing but what doth in ſome reſpect or other
exceed our ſhallow Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings. This is a Rule to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37142:18"/>among all that profeſs themſelves Chriſtians,
whatever God reveals we are to believe; though it be as far above the reach of
our Reaſon, as the Heavens are above the Earth; ſince 'tis impoſſible
for God to Lie, and Blaſphemous for us to ſuppoſe he ſhould; and
worſe to ſuppoſe God to Lie, than to ſuppoſe him not to be; As once
<hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaid, <hi>Malo de me dici nullum eſſe</hi> Plutarchum,
<hi>quam malum</hi> Plutarchum. I had rather, ſaid he, Man ſhould ſay I
am not, than ſay I am wicked. And therefore ſince God hath in his Word
ſet forth the neceſſity of Grace and Faith, in order to our getting to
Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we ought to Believe the one, or to Deſpair of the other.—Some
time ſince I was reading a Book put out by one of the moſt Learned of the
Anabaptiſts; and in that he owns, the Sins of Children are done away; and
that ſome ſuch, if not all ſuch, do go to Heaven; but moſt boldly
affirms, they are not done away in Regeneration. But ſure that Gentleman
would have done well to have told us which way they are cleanſed, and not to
leave ſo many tender-hearted Parents mourning for their deceaſed Infants,
as thoſe without hope, as they muſt needs<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37142:18"/>do if they are
not capable of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or if they cannot tell ſome others way, how
they may be fitted for Heaven. But I perceive that Gentleman was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
none ſhould know his new-found way but himſelf, let the effects be what
they will. But though he is thus unkind, his Dear Brother Mr. C. ſeems to be
a Man of a better Spirit; and though he ſeems to agree with him in the
former, yet he tells us (if we will believe him) how Sin comes to be
deſtroyed in Infants; and that is, ſaith he, by the Righteouſneſs of
Chriſt imputed to them. An Anſwer no doubt pleaſing to the Ignorant
ſort, that will Swallow down any thing, true or falſe, that hath but the
Name of Chriſt, or the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt annexed to it: But
ſure this bold Aſſerter had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20.
<hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony, if any Man</hi> (an Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt not
excepted) <hi>walk not according to this Rule, 'tis becauſe there is no Light
in him;</hi> or rather, I have reaſon to judge, he was reſolved his own
Fancy ſhould guide him in this Matter. Now I would fain know where this
Author can prove from Scripture, any imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs
to any but Believers. I<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37142:19"/>am ſure he cannot; and till he
can, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever fond he or his Brethren may be of his Notion, it not agreeing
with the Rule in God's Word, we are bound to look upon it as ariſing from the
Darkneſs his own deluded Fancy. Since I have been a Student in Divinity, I
have been taught, both out of God's Word, and from our moſt Worthy Authors,
that the imputation of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt had reſpect to the
removal of our Guilt; and that it was the Work of the Spirit within us, to
remove the Filth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Power of Sin. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>By
the waſhing of Regeneration, and renewings of the Hely Ghoſt:</hi> Hence we
are ſaid to be born of the Spirit. Juſtification and Sanctification, though
inſeparable, yet are widely diſtinguiſhed by all but Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and
ſuch as do adhere to them: Sure this Gentleman had ſtrangely forgot the
great difference between our Title to Heaven, and our Meetneſs for Heaven;
unleſs he looks upon our Claim to riſe from our Meetneſs. The
Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, though it gives us a Title to Heaven, as we do
apprehend the Perſon of Chriſt by Faith, yet it doth not take away our
Filth any other way than<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37142:19"/>by way of Purchaſe. 'Tis the
Spirit of God in us that is the Efficient, and that is the thing we are
enquiring into. VVhy then doth this Author thus beguile his unwary Reader, when
he is enquiring how Sin comes to be ſubdued, he tells him how Sin comes to be
pardoned. As if a Pardon to a Malefactor would change his Heart, or as if that
Promiſe of a new Heart added to Forgiveneſs was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of little
worth; I know not what it is to him, I am ſure 'tis precious to all Saints;
what doth this imply, but that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt was imputed to
Infants, to the end they may go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven reeking in Sin; and that they might
be exempted from Regeneration? But to put all out of doubt, I come now to prove
there is a Neceſſity for Infants to have Faith (in the Sence aforeſaid)
if ever they get to Heaven, whatever ſuch bold Men may ſay to the contrary,
who care not how much they ſay, and how little they prove. Let God be true,
tho' all ſuch are found Liars. Now there is a twofold Neceſſity for
Infants to have Faith, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their getting to Heaven, one ariſing from
God's Ordination and Appointment,<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37142:20"/>the other from the
Corruption of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as we come into the VVorld.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> From God's Appointment and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, he hath
made this the way, and the only way to Heaven, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that
believes not ſhall be damned.</hi> I think that is plain Scripture, ſince
'tis ſo defired by the Anabaptiſts; and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion being
Indefinite, is equivolent to a Univerſe. He, that is, any he, High or Low,
Rich or Poor, Adult or Infant. So <hi>John</hi> 3.3,5. <hi>Verily, verily, I
ſay unto thee, except a Man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of
God.</hi> And then adds by way of Explanation, <hi>Except a Man be born of
Water, and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> Now
Regeneration is an Infuſing the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of all Grace into the Soul, as
the Learned <hi>Pemble</hi> obſerves, (one Grace not being the Cauſe of
another,) and if of all Grace, then of Faith, for that is a Grace.</p>
            <p>But perhaps the Anabaptiſts may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that by the Word Man we
are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Adult only, yet at beſt this is but a bare Conjecture,
which in others Caſes is contemned by them; and therefore <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37142:20"/>with their Leave, or without it, I ſhall tye them up to the ſame
Meaſures: For it ſeems unreaſonable to contemn this in others, which we
allow in our ſelves, eſpecially in Matters of Religion; may we not by the
ſame Rule exclude Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? And then I know no Scripture to prove a
Neceſſity for them to be regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. But leſt this ſhould not
ſuffice, (for by this time I may ſuppoſe the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts to be like a
Man drowning, that catches hold of every Straw to keep him from ſinking) I
ſhall therefore prove from Scripture, that the Word Man oft takes in Women
and Children, without Diſtinction of Age or Sex; and to this end I might
multiply Texts, but I ſhall only give you Two for many. The firſt is,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 6.7. <hi>I will deſtroy Man.</hi> Now it is well known that all
the old World was deſtroyed, both Men, Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, excepting thoſe
few in the Ark, and yet only Man is mentioned. So <hi>John</hi> 16.21. <hi>A
Woman, when ſhe is in Travail, hath Sorrow, becauſe her Hour is come; but
as ſoon as ſhe is delivered of the Child, ſhe remembreth no more her
Anguiſh for Joy that a Man is born.</hi> Mind that which in the beginning was
called a<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37142:21"/>Child, is after called a Man; nor can we once
ſuppoſe that we come grown Men immediately out of the Womb; and yet this
may be as eaſily proved as the former. And as the Word Man ſometimes is of
this extent, ſo 'tis moſt evident it is ſo here: For the Word
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Greek ſignifies any one.
<hi>Beza</hi> renders it <hi>Aliquis,</hi> any Body, or any one. But
notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that hath been ſaid, I lately ſaw a Piece,
put out by one of the Ableſt of the Anabaptiſts, in which he will prove
that Chriſt in that Place meant Adult on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and he proves it thus. It muſt
be ſo, becauſe <hi>Nicodemus</hi> underſtood him ſo; but to me it
ſeems ſtrange, that any, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs one as ignorant as <hi>Nicodemus,</hi>
of the new Birth, ſhould think ſuch a blind Idiot as he, a meet Judge of
Chriſt's Meaning; and infallibly to conclude it muſt be ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he
underſtood him ſo, as if <hi>Nicedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was an infallible Judge of
this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. That <hi>Nicedomus</hi> underſtood him ſo I cannot deny; but
if that muſt be his meaning, becauſe he underſtood him ſo, then we
muſt conclude Chriſt meant a natural Birth alſo, for ſo
<hi>Nicodemus</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood him, <hi>Verſe</hi> 4. <hi>Can he enter the
ſecond time into his Mother's Womb,<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37142:21"/>and be born;</hi>
which was a groſs Miſtake, as is clear from <hi>Verſe</hi> 5. Which Words
are a Reproof of his Ignorance and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Conceptions, and an Interpretation
of Chriſt's own Words; and might he not miſtake as to the Subject, as well
as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Nature of the thing? Sure I am that Cauſe is like to be
loſt, that hath no better Witneſs than an ignorant <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> and
we may ſuppoſe the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts at a Loſs, when the ableſt and moſt
learned among them are forced to ſummons in <hi>Nicodemus</hi> as a
Witneſs; for tho' they muſt own him to be a poor Evidence, if they will
believe Chriſt, (<hi>Verſe</hi> 10.) <hi>Art thou a Maſter in</hi>
Iſrael, <hi>and knoweſt not theſe things?</hi> (and they that do not know
things are unmeet to prove them) But either this Perſon put more Confidence
in <hi>Nicodemus</hi> than Chriſt, or elſe knowing his Cauſe was almoſt
gone, would rather cite <hi>Nicodemus</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, he knew neither
what he ſaid, nor whereof he affirmed) rather than have no Witneſs; but
'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee the moſt Learned of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts run into
ſuch groſs Abſurdities, and to be at ſuch a Loſs in ſuch
My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; for if Learning could teach a<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37142:22"/>Man the
Myſteries of the Goſpel, <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> had not been ſo groſly
ignorant of Chriſt's meaning; and I leave it to any Judicious Perſon to
determine, whether we have not as good Ground, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to judge that this
Objecter was of the ſame Mind of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> in underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it
to be a natural Birth, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that becauſe he underſtood it, as
ſpoken of Adult only, therefore it muſt be ſo; for we may ſuppoſe,
had not this Doctor had great Confidence in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of
<hi>Nicodemus,</hi> he would never have ventured that Cauſe which was as dear
to him as his Life upon his ſingle Evidence, and eſpecially in ſuch a
Cauſe, wherein he had ſo many Hundreds op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him; and ſure, had he
judged him in a groſs Miſtake, as to the Nature of that new Birth, he would
never have put ſuch Confidence in what he ſaid with the ſame Breath, as
to the Subject; and as we have infallible Ground to conclude, (from his own
Words) that this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecter is far from believing any Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity or
Poſſibility for Infants to be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, ſo I think I do him no Wrong,
if I ſuppoſe 'tis his Judgment, that there is no more Neceſſity for
grown Perſons<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37142:22"/>to be regenerated; for of this Judgment was
his truſty and well-beloved Friend <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> for had
<hi>Nicodemus</hi> once ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that grown Perſons (any more than
Infants) muſt be born again Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, he would never have mentioned
ſuch a groſs Abſurdity as to be born again Carnally, but taking it for
granted, that Adult (to give the Objecter his Sence) could not be born again
Spiritually, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdly ſuppoſes it to be meant a Carnal Birth; and why we
may not ſuppoſe the Objecter to be of his Judgment in the one, as well as
the other, (eſpecially ſince he puts ſuch Confidence in him) I ſee not;
and now I leave it to my underſtanding Reader to judge, whether we have not
better Ground to believe, that under the Word Men, Children are comprehended,
becauſe the Word ſignifies both, than to conclude Chriſt only meant grown
Men, becauſe <hi>Nicodemus</hi> underſtood him ſo, ſince it is paſt
all diſpute the Word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ſo; but whether <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did
rightly underſtand Chriſt's meaning, may juſtly admit of a Debate; nay,
it ſeems almoſt paſt all Diſpute he did not, by his groſs Miſtake
about other Paſſages relating hereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:37142:23"/>Thus I have, I hope, ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a
Neceſſity for Infants to have Faith, if they get to Heaven, from God's
Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; and what can be more cogent to confirm any Point, than the
expreſs Mind of God? And I am certain, had the Anabaptiſts ſuch-clear
Proof, that no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants ought to be Baptized, as I have given to prove, that
all Infants that get to Heaven muſt have Faith, they would ſoon cry
Victory; nor ſhould I ever hold up my Weapons againſt them, (was it ſo)
leſt haply, by ſo doing, I was found fighting againſt God himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is a Neceſſity for Faith in Infants,
(if they get to Heaven) ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the Corruption of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Which
tho' the Anabaptiſt may probably deny, yet I doubt not but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this
alſo from Scripture. When <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned, by eating the Forbidden
Fruit, he was immediately ſeized with a Spiritual Death, according to the
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, <hi>in the Day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely
die:</hi> And <hi>Adam</hi> being a publick Head and Repreſentative of all
Mankind, this Spiritual Death is intailed <pb n="35" facs="tcp:37142:23"/>on all his
Poſterity. Hence we are ſaid to bear the Image of the Earthly; nor is this
true of Adult only, but of all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>As
in</hi> Adam <hi>all die.</hi> Mind, <hi>all die,</hi> Infants as well as grown
Perſons; and this I ſhall further prove from moſt expreſs Scripture,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And were by Nature the Children of Wrath, even as
others. Gen.</hi> 8.21. <hi>For the Imagination of Man's Heart is evil from his
Youth.</hi> The Evil in our Hearts is the Cauſe of all the Evil in our Lives.
Hence Fooliſhneſs is ſaid to be bound up in the Heart of a Child,
<hi>Prov.</hi> 22.15. It is ſo bound up, that for a while it may not
diſcover it ſelf, yet is in his Heart. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.3. <hi>The
Wicked are eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the Womb, they go aſtray as ſoon as they be
born, ſpeaking Lies:</hi> That is, they have a ſtraying Principle as ſoon
as born. Once more, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Behold I was ſhapen in
Iniquity, and in Sin did my Mother conceive me.</hi> So that by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we not
only want a Title to Heaven, but a Meetneſs alſo, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12.
<hi>Giving Thanks unto the Father, who hath made us meet to be Partakers of
that Inheritance of the Saints in Light:</hi> Implying that by Nature they were
unmeet; and if<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37142:24"/>Children are not thus corrupt by Nature, how
came they to die, ſince the Wages of Sin is Death. Now if Death reigned, as
the Apoſtle ſaith, from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> even over them
that had not ſinned after the Similitude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s
Tranſgreſſion, (that is, Infants that had not ſinned actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) then it
muſt be, becauſe they were Sinners in <hi>Adam,</hi> and had the Seed of
Sin in themſelves habitually, for the Guilt of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Act is not
transferred to any of the meer Sons of Men, but ſuch as partake of his Image
alſo; and I dare be bold to ſay (and can abundantly from Scripture prove)
that the Seed and Spawn of all our Actual Sins are in our Hearts before we
commit one of them; for as in Grace there muſt firſt be the Habit, and then
the Act; ſo in Sin, the Heart is firſt Wicked, then the Life. The Tree is
firſt evil before the Fruit is; ſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.33,35. Now if the
Nature of all is ſo corrupt, as I have proved, then 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for
any thus corrupt to get to Heaven without an inward Change, for what would
Heaven be to an unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Soul? What would the Works of praiſing God be
to one that hates God? Or what would Holy Company be to ſuch 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37142:24"/>as are dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, and to every good
Word and Work reprobate? But leaſt this ſhould not ſuffice, I ſhall
prove from Scripture, that ſuch cannot get to Heaven in an unchanged State, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50. <hi>Now this I ſay, Brethren, that Fleſh and Blood
cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, neither doth Corruption inherit
Incorruption.</hi> VVhere we muſt not underſtand the VVord Fleſh
Phyſical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or in Point of Being; for ſo we believe Chriſt is now in our
Humane Nature in Heaven. VVe believe alſo the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Body,
when the Saints ſhall in their Fleſh ſee God, <hi>Job</hi> 19.26. But
Fleſh here muſt be underſtood morally as corrupted; as <hi>Gal.</hi>
1.16. <hi>Immediately I conferred not with Fleſh and Blood;</hi> in which
Place he means he did not hearken to the corrupt Reaſonings of the Fleſh:
That this is the meaning, ſeems clear; for in the foregoing Verſe he had
been mentioning our Earthly Image, which conſiſts in the Depravity of our
Nature, and then concludes, <hi>That Fleſh and Blood,</hi> that is, ſuch as
retain that Earthly Image, <hi>cannot inherit the Kingdom of God;</hi> ſo
<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Without Holineſs no Man ſhall ſee God,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no one, no Body, as 
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37142:25"/>it ſignifies. Nor is it to be underſtood of actual
Holineſs in our Converſation only; for ſhould a Man die the ſame Moment
that he cloſes with Chriſt, he ſhall as ſurely ſee God to his
Comfort, as if he had liv'd a holy Life never ſo long, our Title to Heaven
ariſing from our Union to Chriſt, and not from our Holineſs, tho' never
ſo great; nor do his good VVorks ſo properly render him meet for Heaven, as
that Holy Principle, from whence they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded: A clear Inſtance we have in
the Thief on the Croſs that was converted, and in Heaven in a few Hours. By
his embracing of Chriſt, he came to have a Title to Heaven, and his inward
Change of Heart rendred him meet for Heaven, notwithſtanding he had no time
to ſpend in a Holy Converſation. From all which it doth appear, that as we
are corrupt by Nature, ſo this Nature, till renewed, can never enter into
Heaven; nor do I ſee what the Anabaptiſts can ſay to this, unleſs they
deny the Corruption of our Nature; and I perceive ſome of them have fled
thither for Refuge: But this is ſo confuted by the former Scriptures, that I
judge it needleſs to add any more; and I cannot but wonder how ſuch as
pretend<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37142:25"/>ſo high an Eſteem for plain Scripture, dare
caſt ſuch Contempt on thoſe many plain Texts I have ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (and more
that I might cite) to prove the Corruption of our Natures, as we come into the
VVold. This gives us ſad ground to Fear, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever high eſteem ſuch
may pretend to plain Scripture, when it ſeems to make for them; yet they
prefer their own Fancies before it, when it really makes againſt them. Thus I
hope I have ſufficiently proved a neceſſity for Infants to have Grace, if
ever they get to Glory. I come now to the cloſe of my Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Minor Propoſition.</hi> But ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants do get to
Heaven. Now I need not ſpend much time to prove his; for I hope the
Anabaptiſts will not be ſo uncharitable as to Sentence all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants to
Eternal Deſtruction, rather than receive the Truth of the Goſpel: And
indeed I find ſome of them ſo far from denying that ſome Infants get to
Heaven, that they rather believe that none miſs of Heaven. But if any of the
reſt of the Anabaptiſts ſhould ſo far differ from their Brethren as to 
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37142:26"/>deny it, yet 'tis our comfort the Scripture doth in moſt
expreſs words affirm it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. <hi>Of ſuch is the Kingdom of
Heaven;</hi> not that the Kingdom of Heaven conſiſts only of ſuch, but
that ſome ſuch are of that Kingdom. By the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaith
<hi>Marlorate,</hi> we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Eternal Felicity of the Elect.
Some indeed underſtand it of the viſible Kingdom of Chriſt on Earth: But
ſuch do not underſtand it ſo in oppoſition to their Eternal Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
and indeed if ſome of ſuch as are in Chriſt's Viſible Kingdom here on
Earth do not get to Heaven, I know not who ſhall come there, Viſible not
being oppoſed to Inviſible; but only diſtinguiſhed from it. So that
ſince ſome ſuch do get to Heaven (as I have proved) but none get to
Heaven with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Renovation, hence it unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly follows, ſome ſuch are
renewed; which Renovation takes in the Seeds or Habit of Faith, and all other
Graces. And thus have I confirmed my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I am confident ſtands
ſo firm on Scripture ground, that the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail
againſt<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37142:26"/>it. All I ſhall add ſhall be to Anſwer
ſome Objections that may be made by ſome againſt it; though indeed the
truth is ſo clear, that Objections are not worthy to be heard, much leſs to
to be anſwered. But to the End that things may be made plain to the
mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt capacity, and nothing wanting for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to ſuch as
deſire it, I proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. We ſee no ſuch Ground to hope ſuch have
Grace. Do not we ſee that oft-times the Children of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents prove
wicked; which they would not have done, if they had Grace in Infancy, unleſs
they fall from Grace; which we may ſuppoſe you do not Believe.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That ſome Children of Believing Parents do
prove Graceleſs and Wicked, by too ſad experience we find true: Nor can we
from hence infer, that ſuch fall from Grace; for I know none that hold that
all ſuch have Grace, I mean of Unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Infants; for as to Baptized
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, the Papiſts and Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> both hold, That all
ſuch have<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37142:27"/>Grace; though for my own part, tho' I hope well
of all ſuch as are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, <hi>de jure,</hi> of right; yet to affirm that
all ſuch have Grace, I dare not; neither do I think any from Scripture have
good ground ſo to do. Should none have Grace (among the Seed of Believers)
but ſuch as Die in Infancy, or who do in time appear Gracious, but know not
ſo exactly the time of their Converſion, who may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be
wrought upon in Infancy, they would amount to a vaſt number: And perhaps as
many by the Rule of Proportion as may be found to have Grace (in the great Day,
when all muſt be weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary) in our particular
Churches. But if we muſt not hope of any, becauſe ſome prove wicked; what
ſhall we ſay of Adult Profeſſors, who are Members in Churches? Do not
many of them prove Hypocrites? Muſt the Eleven therefore be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for
Hypocrites, becauſe a <hi>Judas</hi> was among them? Would not this be to
Judge before the time? Sure I am, at this rate, we muſt hope of none, Adult
or Infants. But if you ſay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37142:27"/>ſome
profeſſors prove Wicked, yet we are to hope well of others, till ſuch
time as their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs diſcovers it ſelf: So ſay I as to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants;
though ſome prove wicked, yet till others appear ſo, we ought to hope well
of them, if we ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that doth cut off our hope; and not ſo to do
muſt be judged the greateſt uncharitableneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oject.</hi> 2. But Adult Perſons make a Profeſſion of
Chriſt, ſo do not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All their Profeſſion is but the ground of our
hope of an inward Change; and was it poſſible to ſee the Heart unrenewed:
Whatever Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſuch a one might make, it would be a Sin to Baptize
ſuch a one. So that if we have but good ground to hope they have Faith, be it
by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, or otherwiſe it matters not. If the Objecter ſay, 'tis
his bare Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gives a right, then they give away the cauſe they
have ſo contended for; ſince Faith and Profeſſion are not only
diſtinct, but ſeparable. If they ſay,<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37142:28"/>Faith gives them
a right, this makes for me; as I have proved: If they ſay, 'tis Faith as
Profeſſed, and no otherways, this is evidenly to lay more ſtreſs upon
their Profeſſion than Faith; ſince whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver other ground we have to hope
they have Faith, yet without a Profeſſion of that Faith, they muſt not be
Baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. This makes Baptiſm a Regenerating Ordinance,
which is not a Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have reaſon to think this a meer Cavil, and a
wilful Miſtake of the Objecter. For my own part, tho' I am for
Infant-Baptiſm (and am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded from Scripture I have good reaſon
ſo to be) yet I muſt again declare, I am far from approving of that
Popiſh Doctrine, that Baptiſm conferrs Grace from any Vertue in it; though
I cannot deny but God may work Grace in ſome in that Ordinance.</p>
            <p>I believe ſome have Grace that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were Baptized; and that
ſome are Baptized that never had Grace, both of Adult as well as Infants: Nor
doth our practice give the leaſt countenance to believe that this Ordinance
Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerates. Nay it ſeems clearly to hold<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37142:28"/>forth the
contrary, ſince I do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Baptize to the end they may be
Regenerated; but in hopes they are already ſo. There muſt firſt be a
Right before they partake of the Seal But I expect ſome ſhould ſay, to
what end ſhould Parents bring their Children to this Ordinance, if they hope
they are Regenerated before? <hi>Anſwer,</hi> If the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecter be an
Anabaptiſt, I anſwer him, to the ſame end they bring their Adult, whom
they own to be Believers; but if of another Judgment, I anſwer, to the ſame
end Adult Believers come to the Lord's Supper after they are in Chriſt; and
that which will ſerve for an Anſwer to the one, may ſerve as an
ſufficient Anſwer to the other. There may be a neceſſity of doing a
thing in order to our avoiding Sin, when there is not a neceſſity to do the
ſame in order to avoiding of Hell. For inſtance, A Saint is bound in his
own Perſon to fulfil the Moral Law perfectly, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his avoiding Sin,
but not in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his avoiding Hell: If he was, who then could be ſaved?
And if no other Reaſon can be given, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God will have it ſo,
'tis ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37142:29"/>to juſtifie our practice: But to this I
add, <hi>(ex abundanti)</hi> that as a grown Perſon, who hath Grace, ſtands
in need of Prayer, Preaching, and the Lord's Supper, for to ſtrengthen his
Grace, they being appointed to that end: So though we were ſure Infants had
ſuch Faith as we Baptize, yet we ought to Baptize them, for the
ſtrengthening of that Faith, and to look on it as our Priviledge as well as
Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 4. If we may Baptize In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants on this ground,
then we may Baptize the Infants of Unbelieving Parents; for we have the ſame
ground to hope of them: And further, we find ſuch were Circumciſed; but you
do not Baptize ſuch, therefore you ought not to Baptize others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though I cannot deny but ſome ſuch may be
Saved, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently muſt have Grace; yet this no way weakens my
Argument laid down, as I ſhall prove by another Argument, thus,—Thoſe
to whom God hath made ſpecial Promiſes, of them we have ſpecial ground to
hope: But the<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37142:29"/>Infant Seed of Believers are ſuch to whom
God hath made ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; therefore of ſuch we have ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
ground to hope. The Major is clear: For though we cannot from hence infallibly
conclude the certainty of the Salvation of all ſuch, (the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
reſpecting the External, as well as Internal part of the Covenant) yet ſure
I am ſuch Promiſes give more ground to hope, than where he hath made none;
and for any to deny this, is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than to charge God with mocking of his
Dear Children; ſince in their Judgment all the Promiſes God hath made to
their Seed, will not afford ſufficient ground ſo much as to hope concerning
their future Happineſs. And ſure I am, if there is no ground to hope of
them, there is none of others; and ſo all muſt (in their Judgment)
periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Minor Propoſition.</hi> But God hath made ſpecial
Promiſes to the Seed of Believers. <hi>Firſt,</hi> He hath made Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
unto ſuch, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7,8. <hi>And I will eſtabliſh my Covenant
between thee and me, and thy Seed after thee in<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37142:30"/>their
Generations, for an Everlaſting Covenant, to be a God to thee, and thy Seed
after thee.</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>For the Promiſe is to you and to
your Children,</hi> &amp;c. Which Promiſe being renewed in the New
Teſtament, and ſo many hundred Years after it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to
<hi>Abraham,</hi> proves it was no bare Promiſe of the Land of
<hi>Canaan,</hi> as ſome vainly ſuppoſe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſay,
ſpecial Promiſes; I mean ſuch as are not made in common to the Seed of
Unbelievers; and I challenge any to ſhew me one ſuch promiſe made to
them. For though I cannot deny but ſome ſuch may be Saved; yet I ſee no
more ground to hope of ſuch dying in Infancy, than of the Infants of
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; there being no more Promiſe to the former than the latter,
according to the beſt of my knowledge, in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Nor can we conclude,
(as was Objected) that becauſe the Seed of Unbelievers as well as Believers
were Circumciſed, (ſuppoſe it ſo); that therefore the Seed of all, both
Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as well as Believers, muſt be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, no more than we can
conclude, that 'tis lawful for Women to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize,<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37142:30"/>becauſe
<hi>Zipporah</hi> Circumciſed her Son. There was no fixed Officer in the
Jewiſh Church (as Mr. <hi>Strong</hi> hath obſerved) to adminiſter that
Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; and then no wonder if there was ſome Male-adminiſtration as to
the Subject: But ſuppoſe it was the Will of God it ſhould be ſo in that
Day, it doth not follow it muſt be ſo now: Though Baptiſm comes in the
room of Circumciſion, for the ſame God that had power to Change the Seal,
may, if he will, Change or Limit the Subject alſo. But is Objected by ſome,
That the Promiſes were not made to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natural Seed, but
Spiritual. For 'tis ſaid, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>If ye are Chriſt's, then
are ye</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Seed, and Heirs according to Promiſe.</hi> And from
hence conclude, there is no ground to Baptize the Natural Seed of Believers as
Believers; becauſe the Promiſe is not made to them as Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seed. To
which I Anſwer, Had this Objection been brought againſt the Corrupt
Practice of ſuch as Baptize the Infants of ſuch Parents as are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Prophane (for 'tis evident Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was firſt inſtituted to
Believing<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37142:31"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi>) I think it would have been
unanſwerable, becauſe there is nothing of Chriſt appears in ſuch
Parents; no, not ſo much as a Profeſſion; and how ſuch Infants can be
ſuppoſed to ſtand in the Place, or partake of the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of
<hi>Abraham,</hi> unleſs one of their Parents ſtood in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s
room, I ſee not. But ſince the Objection is made againſt ſuch as only
Baptize ſuch as have Believing Parents, I muſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Anſwer, The
forecited Scripture ſeems not in the leaſt to oppoſe the Truth I have
laid down; as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if we conſider the Apoſtle is there ſpeaking
to Adult Gentiles; and doth aſſure them, that though they were not the
Natural Seed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and ſo could not on that account lay claim
to the Promiſe, either to themſelves or Children, as they might have done
had they been ſo; and their Converſations had been becoming the the
Goſpel of Chriſt, yet by Virtue of their Relation to Chriſt, or their
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in Chriſt, (though not of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Natural Seed) they
ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Priviledges: And as at the firſt, the
Promiſe was made<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37142:31"/>to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, ſo
when the Gentiles came to initiate the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Promiſe
ſhould be to them and their Seed, as it was to <hi>Abraham.</hi> Now the
Promiſe at firſt reached unto <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natural Seed, as is clear
from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7,8,9,10. Now we cannot ſuppoſe the Seal to be
applied to any but ſuch as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was made to. But ſuch as were
Eight Days Old were Circumciſed; therefore to ſuch the Promiſe was made:
For though I grant that all in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Houſe were Circumciſed,
both Old and Young; the Adult being ſuch, as we may ſuppoſe, were at
leaſt Profeſſors: For 'tis ſaid of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> he would teach
his Houſe; yet it is evident none were excepted, if but Eight Days old. So
that this Text ſtrongly confirms my Argument; for if upon our Believing we
come to be <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and to partake of his Bleſſedneſs, as
in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.9. then it follows by an undeniable conſequence, that as
the Promiſe at firſt was made to Believing <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his
Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seed, ſo it muſt he continued to us Believers, and our Seed; or
elſe we<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37142:32"/>are not Bleſſed as <hi>Abraham;</hi> for it
was no ſmall part of his Bleſſedneſs that the Promiſe extended to his
Seed. But to put all out of doubt, if the Promiſe was made to a Spiritual
Seed, then it muſt be to ſuch as we are ſure are Spiritual, or to ſuch
as we have good ground to hope are ſo. If you ſay the former, then we
muſt Baptize none, either Old or Young; becauſe (as I have proved) we
can-never infallibly tell who are Spiritual, it being only proper to God, who
is the Father of Spirits, to know that: But if you ſay the latter; that is,
ſuch as we have good ground to hope are Spiritual, then the Infant Seed of
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers muſt come in; ſince I hope I have ſufficiently proved we have
good ground to hope ſuch are inwardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed; and if ſuch as are renewed
and born again by the Spirit, and have the Image of God Engraven on their
Hearts, may not be reckoned for a Spiritual Seed, I know not who muſt. So
that till my former Argument is overthrown concerning the neceſſity for
Infants to be Regenerated, and the good ground we have to hope ſome are ſo
on the account of the Promiſes made to them;<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37142:32"/>I ſay, till
then all that is here added is of no Force.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 5. But we have no Inſtance in Scripture of any
Infants ever Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; therefore we have ground to think ſuch ought not to
be Baptized, for we cannot ſuppoſe the Apoſtles were wanting in their
Duty in that Caſe.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, Tho' we have no expreſs Inſtance of any
Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, yet we have ſome Texts, that will, I conceive, infallibly
prove ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſome then were Baptized, or at leaſt now ought to be
Baptized. 'Tis ſaid of the Jaylor, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.33. <hi>He was Baptized,
he and all his ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Now we have good Ground to believe, that
all his takes in Children, and that ſome of theſe all were little Children,
or at leaſt ſo ſmall, as not to be able to make a Profeſſion of their
Faith; but ſuppoſe they were able, yet there is no expreſs mention made
that they did ſo before they were Baptized. 'Tis ſaid, indeed he ſpake to
them the Word of the Lord;<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37142:33"/>but we cannot from thence
conclude, they that heard believed; 'tis ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, after that he
rejoiced, believing in God with all his Houſe, but this was after he and all
his were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. But there is one Text more that will be as a ſharp
two-edged Sword, which will wound the Anabaptiſts, let them defend
themſelves with all the Subtilty they can. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15. of <hi>Lydia,
And when ſhe was Baptized, and her Houſhold, &amp;c.</hi> Now the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry
is, who this Houſhold were? But let them be who they will, yet the
Anabaptiſt will not reckon little Children among them, becauſe none ſuch
are mention'd; but if ſo, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neither Husband, Servant, nor
Kindred, are mentioned, therefore there was none. And thus the Anabaptiſts
have (by an Art never before heard of) reduced this Houſhold to juſt no
Body but <hi>Lydia,</hi> and her ſelf; but I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (and I can do
no other) that in this Houſhold there were more than <hi>Lydia.</hi> And,
<hi>Firſt,</hi> I will ſuppoſe ſome of them Children, as I have good
ground to do, from the uſe of the Word in Scripture; and I find ſome of 
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37142:33"/>the Anabaptiſts do not deny this, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay
<hi>Lydia</hi> was too old to have young Children. Now if there was any young
Children in this Houſhold, as we have ground to ſuppoſe, then here we
have an Inſtance of ſuch Baptized; but I will ſuppoſe, thoſe Children
of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s, as the Anabaptiſts affirm to be grown up; then I ask by
what Claim they were Baptized? Now that her Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold were Baptized, the Word
expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirms; if they ſay, as they were Profeſſors, I deny that,
and it lyes on them to prove it; there is not one Word of their believing, or
any of them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or after they were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; and had they made any
Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, we have ground to think ſome mention would have been made of
it; but ſince the Scripture is ſilent, tho' the Anabaptiſts ſhould
never ſo boldly affirm it, yet I am confident ſcarce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but thoſe of
their own Perſwaſion, will in the leaſt regard what they ſay. If they
were Baptized, as being rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Lydia,</hi> tho' they made no
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion themſelves, then this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws the Practice of the
Anabaptiſts; ſince here are ſome Baptized that made<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37142:34"/>no
Profeſſion of their Faith; and alſo it gives us the Cauſe, by an
undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Concluſion; for if ſuch Children as are Adult, but no
Profeſſors, yet have a Right to Baptiſm on the Account of their Relation
to a Parent that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; then it follows, that what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to any
Child, meerly as the Child of ſuch a Parent, belongs to all the Children of
the ſame a Parent: But it may be ſome may ſay this Houſhold were all
Servants; but if they were, yet here is not a Word of their Faith or
Profeſſion: And then I conclude, that if <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Servants were
Baptized, by Vertue of that Relation to <hi>Lydia,</hi> much more ſhould her
Children be Baptized, ſtanding in a nearer Relation to her. Thus I have
ſhown you there are ſome Texts that afford us good ground to think ſome
Infants or little Children were Baptized; but yet if there were not any ſuch
therein contained, yet the ſame Scriptures do afford undeniable
Conſequences, that ſome Infants have a Right to Baptiſm, as I have proved
at large. But ſuppoſe no Inſtance in Scripture could be given of an
Infant Baptized, or any thing like it; yet if<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37142:34"/>I prove from
Scripture they ought to be, it is a ſufficient Warrant for us ſo to do; and
I conceive I ſhall extort a Conſent to this from my Brethren from this
following Conſideration, That there was a time when no Inſtance could be
produced of any Adult that had been Baptized; I mean, in its firſt
Inſtitution; as <hi>Abraham</hi> could produce no Inſtance of any that had
been Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. Now then according to this Rule none muſt be
Circumciſed or Baptized, becauſe no Inſtance could then be produced of
any that had; but you muſt ſay, Tho' no Inſtance could be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of any
Adult that had been Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, yet when God made it known to be his Will, that
ſo it ſhould be, it was ſufficient to juſtifie their Practice in ſo
doing. So ſay I as to Infants, tho' no Inſtance could be given of any
Infant that had been Baptized, yet if God hath made it known to us in his Word,
ſuch ought to be, it is a ſufficient War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to us ſo to do; and whether
I have proved ſome Infants Right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm from Scripture, I leave it
unto any Underſtanding, Impartial, and Unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced Reader to judge; and I
muſt<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37142:35"/>tell you, if I have proved their Right to this
Ordinance, it is far more than if I could produce an Inſtance, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Inſtances, of ſuch as had; for Right will be Right; but 'tis poſſible
the beſt of Men (being imperfect) may fail as to ſome particular Fact.
Hence we ſay, <hi>a facto ad jus non valet Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> that is, we
cannot from the Fact conclude the Right of the thing. We are not to imitate
<hi>David</hi> in his Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor <hi>Peter</hi> in his denying Chriſt,
tho' the one was a Prophet, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Apoſtle. For tho' it cannot be
denied that they did ſo, yet the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture proves they ought not to have
done ſo; and if the Apoſtles in Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Adult, and not Baptizing
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, (ſuppoſe it to be ſo) did not do the former, and omit doing the
latter, upon the Account of the Right the one had, and want of a Right to the
other, tho' you could produce a Thouſand Inſtances, we are no more bound to
imitate them, than to imitate <hi>David</hi> in his Adultery, or <hi>Peter</hi>
in Curſing and Swearing; becauſe we are not to live by Examples, but Laws;
nay, as notwithſtanding ſuch ſad Inſtances<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37142:35"/>in
Scripture, we have Liberty, and are bound (not only not to imitate them, but)
to act contrary thereunto; ſo could you prove, that the Apoſtles ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
Baptized one Infant; yet if I can prove from Scripture, (as I hope I have) they
ought to be Baptized, we ought in this to act contrary to their Practice, and
not make one Sin an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let into another; ſince the Right of the thing is more
than if you could produce as many Inſtances as there are Stars in the
Firmament without this Right. Let not any think I do this to reflect on the
Practice of the Bleſſed Apoſtles, God forbid; for I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent they
were not wanting in the due Adminiſtration of any Ordinance in God's Houſe;
but I do it to ſhew, that the Right of this Ordinance is more than barely the
Action; and that you may ſee how unreaſonable it ſeems in the
Anabaptiſts to make ſuch a noiſe about one Infant Baptized, when we can
produce that which is more than a Thouſand Inſtances, ſimply
conſidered; the Apoſtles did firſt conſider their Right before they
Baptized any.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37142:36"/>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 6. But we find no Command in
Scripture to Baptize ſuch, and ſo have good ground to believe it is not the
Mind of God ſuch ſhould be Baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is no need of a Poſitive Command, or an
Expreſs Scripture, in ſo many plain Words to affirm a thing, in order to
the proving a Duty or Truth. We have a Matter of as great Concern, as the
Baptiſm of Old or Young, proved by Chriſt himſelf by a bare
Conſequence, and that is the Reſurrection. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.31,32. <hi>But
as touching the Reſurrection of the Dead, have ye not read that which was
ſpoken to you of God, ſaying, I am the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God
of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob: <hi>God is not the God of the
Dead, but of the Living.</hi> This Scripture he cites from <hi>Ex.</hi> 3.6. to
prove the Reſurrection, and yet not one Word of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction mentioned
in it, but proves it by Conſequence thus; That becauſe God is the God of
<hi>Abraham,</hi> but not the God of the Dead; therefore <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> 
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37142:36"/>muſt live, not only in his Soul, but the Body, they both
making up but the whole of <hi>Abraham.</hi> And if nothing muſt be received
as a Truth, but what we have a plain Scripture for in ſo many Words, how will
my Friends, the Anabaptiſts, prove, That the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is
imputed to any of us, ſince (tho' we have Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures that will prove it as
to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, of it yet) I know no Scripture, which in ſo many plain
Words doth affirm it, but perhaps ſome of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts will rather
reject this as a Truth, than admit of Infant Baptiſm; and as to Doctrines,
ſo in Point of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. There is no Neceſſity of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Command to
make it a Duty; to illuſtrate this, if God command us to be Charitable to
poor Saints, tho' the Command makes no mention of any expreſly by Name, yet
when we ſee ſuch in Wants, we are bound to relieve them, and cannot omit
it, (if able) without Sin; it will not excuſe us to ſay, I am not commanded
to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſuch by Name; ſo tho' Sinners are not called by Name to come to
Chriſt, 'tis their Duty to come; ſo<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37142:37"/>when God commands us
to Baptize all ſuch as we have good ground to hope are Believers, if ſome
Infants are found in that number, we are as much bound to Baptize them as any
others, as if mentioned by Name. God once commanded Circumciſion to the Jews
and their Infant Seed; but if in the New Teſtament he hath declared (as I
have ſhown) that we come in the Jews room, and that Baptiſm comes in the
room of Circumciſion, that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Circumciſing Infants doth as much
enjoin the Baptizing of Infants: And no wonder Infants are not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
expreſly in the New Teſtament, as the Subjects of Baptiſm; for ſince
Baptiſm comes in the room of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, the Subjects of that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
were ſo well known, they need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to be again mentioned; if an expreſs
Command is ſo neceſſary, I would know what Command the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts can
produce (or inſtance ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) for to Baptize by Dipping. I am certain they
can produce no ſuch Command in Scripture; but they will reply, Tho' they have
neither Precept or Preſident, yet becauſe the Word<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37142:37"/>ſignifies ſo, therefore they do it ſo, ſay I, (to ſay
nothing now, how variouſly that Word is uſed) as to Baptizing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants.
Tho' we have no expreſs Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in ſo many Words or Preſident, yet
becauſe we have many Words, and great part of ſome Chapters too in
Scripture, that ſignifie to us that ſome Infants have been, and ought to be
Baptized, therefore I do it; and why Significations and Meanings in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
may not be allowed to us as well as them, I ſee not.</p>
            <p>And thus, having produced plain Scripture for Infant Baptiſm,
(ſince nothing leſs will do) or at leaſt I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as plain as can be
produced to Baptize Adult, I ſhall conclude this Point (touching the Subject)
with a reaſonable Requeſt to my Chriſtian Friend the Anabaptiſts, which
is, that either they would receive the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine laid down, or give ſome
plain Scripture, to prove ſomething of what I have laid down to be falfe; and
if they will not comply with my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that which I have often feared will
too evidently appear to be a Truth,<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37142:38"/>that it is Love to a
Party (more than to the Truth) that hath made them ſo earneſtly contend; I
have often obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, 'tis no eaſie Matter to convince ſome Men of Truth;
when they have been accuſtomed to Error, they ſcorn to be informed by
others; the Pride of their Hearts makes them ſhut their Eyes, that they will
not ſee; (and we ſay none are ſo blind as they that will not ſee) and
if this Spirit, or Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, do not prevail with my Reader, I hope he and I
ſhall be both of one Mind for the time to come, which will be the Joy of my
Heart; yet not ſo much, that I have gained the Cauſe I have been contending
for, as that this unhappy Controverſie is like to be ended, and my Friends,
the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, brought to the Acknowledgment of the Truth, as it is in
Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Having finiſhed my Diſcourſe as to the Subject of Baptiſm,
I deſigned at firſt to proceed no further, but to the end that nothing may
be wanting, for the full Satisfaction of ſuch as deſire it, about the whole
of Baptiſm, I ſhall make ſome brief Enquiry as to <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37142:38"/>the
manner how this Ordinance ought to be Adminiſtred, whether by Dipping only,
or otherwiſe; for I never expect that the Anabaptiſts ſhould reſignup
their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Errors, ſo long as they have any thing which looks like a
Strong Hold to ſhelter them: And therefore knowing how earneſtly they
contend about the Manner how, as well as the Subject who, I ſhall a little
inſiſt on that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And though perhaps my Reader may cry Victory before
he read any further, yet I would deſire him to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Boaſting, at
leaſt till he put off the Harneſs; leſt all that hear him in the end
Laugh at him. Now the Grand Plea of the Anabaptiſts for Dipping is, the word
in the Original ſignifies ſo: But what if the only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to them in this
Caſe, ſhould be the ſame they give to us in other Caſes? Give me a
plain Scripture, ſince, Significations, and doubtful Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, are of no
force with them: But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring my Reader to the late <hi>Portſmouth</hi>
Diſputation about the Signification of the word, by Mr. <hi>Chandler,</hi>
&amp;c. not being willing to trouble my Reader with any thing of this Nature in
my<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37142:39"/>Book which he may read in another: I ſhall keep to
plain Scripture, ſince that is moſt like to convince the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of
Readers, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, if the Greek word
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as it is uſed by Chriſt and
his Apoſtles, (whom we muſt ſuppoſe well knew how to uſe proper words
to expreſs their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) can with any ſhew of reaſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
ſignifies Dipping under Water; but to prevent all miſtakes, (and that the
difference may not be by any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be greater than it is) if it be
enquired, whether it may not in ſome caſe be lawful to Baptize by Dipping?
I grant it may; but the Queſtion is, whether we may not as lawfully Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize
ſome other way? This the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts deny, and I affirm; and hope I
ſhall prove by theſe following Texts, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.5. John <hi>Baptized
with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Now, while 'tis ſaid with Water, not in Water, it ſeems
to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply he did not Dip them, only made uſe of Water in that Ordinance; for
how improper would it be to ſay, I Dipped ſuch a thing with Water? But not
at all to ſay I waſh'd, ſuch a thing with Water, when we only ſprinkle
it, <pb n="67" facs="tcp:37142:39"/>or throw Water upon it: See another Text, <hi>Mark</hi>
7.4. <hi>And when they come from the Market, unleſs they waſh they Eat
not.</hi> Thoſe words, <hi>unleſs they waſh,</hi> are
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, unleſs they Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize; and the
Words of Tables in the end of the Verſe is,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Beds: Now it is ſcarce
conſiſtent with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſuppoſe that they ſhould ſo
fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently dip their Beds: If they did, we may ſuppoſe them very unfit to
lye on for ſome time. The Phariſees had ſuch a proud conceit of
themſelves, that they thought if they did but deal with others they are
defiled by ſo doing; and therefore after they came from the Market, they were
to waſh their Hands with which they had delivered any thing to, or received
any thing from others; but that they ſhould on all ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Dip
themſelves wholly under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſeems to be both incredible and ridiculous;
and yet this is in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal called a Baptizing, as you have heard. All I
have found anſwered to this, is, that in waſhing they Dipped their Hands,
and ſo it was Dipping ſtill, though not the whole Body: To which I
anſwer, In waſhing our Hands <pb n="68" facs="tcp:37142:40"/>we are not wont to Dip
them, unleſs ſome part of them: So that all they can from hence inferr, is,
that ſome little part of the Body ought to be Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in Baptiſm, as much
as the Hands or Fingers end; why then do the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts impoſe Dipping
the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and hazard the Life by ſo doing, when it might as well be
ſome little Part of the Body only? If they love Peace, why do they not ſhew
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves willing to comply with us as far as they can with a good
Conſcience, ſince they are forced from this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to own there is no
neceſſity from the ſignification of the Word, to Dip or Plung the whole
Body under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Another Text to be conſidered, is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. <hi>And
where all Baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Clouds, and in the Sea.</hi>
But can we ſuppoſe they were dipped in the Cloud? On the other hand, doth
not the falling of the Rain from a Cloud moſt exactly anſwer to our manner
of Baptizing? The chief Reply I have met with to this, is, That if the Cloud
rained on them while they were going<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37142:40"/>through the Sea, then
they could not be ſaid to go through on dry Ground, as the Text affirms. To
which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, They that are ſo careful of the Senſe of the Text in one
thing, ſhould alſo of another; for as it is ſaid, <hi>They went through
on dry Ground;</hi> ſo it is ſaid, <hi>They were Baptized in the
Cloud;</hi> and ſure it muſt mean, ſome Water came from the Cloud, either
to plunge them, or to waſh them, or elſe how could it be called Baptiſm?
Can any be Baptized without Water? I doubt not but if this Scripture would but
have countenanced Dipping, as well as ſome other Waſhing, the
Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts would never have ſtood on the dry Ground. But what a poor
Reply is this, That the Rain could not fall on them; becauſe 'tis ſaid,
<hi>They went on dry Ground?</hi> As if that Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God who made a Way for
them through the Deep, that the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (even to a Miracle) ſtood as a Wall to
defend them, could not cauſe alſo that the Ground ſhould be dry,
notwithſtanding ſome ſhower might Fall. As if he that dried up the Ocean,
could not alſo dry up<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37142:41"/>ſome Drops. Suppoſe the Rain
from the Cloud did fall on the Ground, might they notwithſtanding go on dry
Ground? Yes ſure, without a Miracle: We read <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.14. <hi>The
Earth was Dried;</hi> where the Word Dry, is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the Flood, and not
to all Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; for it is ſcarce credible, in an ordinary Way, that after
the Earth had been ſo long ſoaked by ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Flood, it
ſhould within ſo few Days be ſo dried, that it ſhould not have ſo
much Moiſture as a ſmall ſhower of Rain might occaſion. When 'tis
ſaid the Earth was dryed, it ſhews that the Flood was ſo far gone that
they might walk upon it. So the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> though ſome Rain might
fall on them, yet might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to go on dry Ground; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no
doubt but the dry Ground is oppoſed to the Sea, that was wont to overflow
that place.</p>
            <p>See what poor ſhifts the Ableſt of the Anabaptiſts are
forced to make uſe of to ſupport their tottering Cauſe: Sure I am, it
gives any rational Man cauſe to ſuppoſe they are at a loſs, 
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37142:41"/>when they can make no better a Reply than thus: See on what
ſlender Grounds they can oppoſe the plaineſt Scripture when it makes
againſt them; as if they were reſolved to follow their own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, let
the Scripture ſay what it will. Thus you ſee the Word will juſtifie our
way of Baptizing; and if ſo, then the Anabaptiſts can never juſtifie
their Separation from us, or Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies againſt us on that Acount: But
becauſe there are ſome Scriptures which are urged as preſidents of
Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Baptized by Dipping, I ſhall therefore weigh them in the Ballance,
and ſee if they are not wanting, to that End for which they are brought. The
firſt Text I ſhall mention is <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. where we are ſaid to be
buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm; and ſo they conclude, that as Perſons
when Buried are put under the Earth, ſo when Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are Baptized, they
ſhould be put wholly under the Water. But here they would do well to
conſider this is but a Metaphor; and 'tis a known Maxim, Similitudes will not
run on all four; but if this Metaphor muſt hold good in all things, then let
the Anabaptiſts<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37142:42"/>be careful that the Party Baptized lye as
long under the Water, as the Dead do under the Earth, before they Riſe again;
but if you ſay the compariſon will not hold good in that, then by your own
Confeſſion not in all; and ſo proves nothing to the point: But if a
Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial may ſerve to ſet forth Baptiſm, this makes for us; for as in
Burying a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they throw the Earth upon him; ſo we in Baptiſm throw
the Water on the Party Baptized. Another Text is, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. <hi>And
they went both down into the Water;</hi> and ſo draw a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, (ſuch
a one as it is) that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he went down, therefore he was Dipped: But here
I muſt remind my Friends this is not a plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to prove Dipping; nor
will it afford any more than a poor conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, (ſuch as I am ſure they
would reject with the greateſt ſcorn and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion, if brought againſt
them) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, becauſe one went into the Water, therefore under the
Water with their whole Bodies, when they might as truly be ſaid to go into
the Water, if their Feet were but in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as if under the Water with their whole Body;<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37142:42"/>and
no wonder that 'tis ſaid, they went down, ſince Water uſually lyes in
ſome bottom; and they that will have it, muſt go down for it. But now that
this going down was not a Dipping, is ſo clear even from the Text it ſelf,
that all that do not wilfully ſhut their Eyes, muſt needs ſee it. 'Tis
ſaid, <hi>They went both down;</hi> and what is ſaid of the one is (in that
reſpect) ſaid of the other. So that if from hence it can be proved that the
Eunuch was Dipped, it proves that <hi>Philip</hi> was Dipped alſo: From
whence I frame an unanſwerable Argument from the Words, that the Eunuch was
not Dipped. Thus the Eunuch went down no more under Water than
<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip:</hi> But <hi>Philip</hi> was not Dipped, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the
Eunuch. The Major is clear, for 'tis ſaid, <hi>both went down;</hi> and if
any Scripture can be produced to prove the Eunuch went lower into the Water
than <hi>Philip,</hi> I will believe it: But ſure I am this Text is ſilent,
nay, it ſeems to ſpeak the contrary; for 'tis ſaid, <hi>both went
down;</hi> which Words ſeem to imply, both went equally down. The Minor I
conceive<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37142:43"/>will by moſt readily be granted, that
<hi>Philip</hi> was not Dipped: And before I would have the Anabaptiſts
believe he was, I deſire them to prove it; but though I doubt not but they
can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce many Inſtances of Baptized Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Dipped among themſelves;
yet I am ready to believe ſhould they ſearch the World through, they could
not produce one inſtance of an Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Dipped. If they think
<hi>Philip</hi> was Dipped, why do not they then imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him? That the
Baptizer, as well as Baptized are Dipped. But do they thus? No, <hi>they bind
heavy Burthens to lay on others Shoulders, but care not for bearing any part
themſelves.</hi> But I wonder how ſuch as pretend to walk ſo exactly by
Scripture Rule, dare thus mangle it, while they force it to ſpeak in what
Langnage they would have it; while they readily embrace what of it ſeems to
make for them, and in the mean time trample under Foot what doth really make
againſt them. They own that <hi>Philip</hi> was not Dipped: The Text ſays
not one word of the Eunuch's going lower than he, into the Water, but much
rather proves the contrary;<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37142:43"/>and yet notwithſtanding all
that this, Scripture ſpeaks againſt it. Such is the Love of the
Anabaptiſts to Dipping, that the poor Eunuch, will he, nill he, down under
VVater he muſt go, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes of him. He went down into the Water for
his own Profit and Pleaſure, and they will force him down under the Water for
theirs; but I'll ſoon bring him up again, if they will but have Patience to
ſtand by till I open another Word in that Text. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>Both went
down.</hi> Mind, both were active in going down; from whence I form an Argument
to prove this going down was not Dipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>g in Baptiſm; thus in Baptiſm the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y Baptized is paſſive; but in this the Eunuch was not
paſſive; therefore in that Action of going down
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was not Baptized: So that in
Baptiſm the Party to be baptized is paſſive. I need not ſtand to prove,
ſince I know none that do affirm that a Perſen may in Baptiſm Dip
himſelf: And if going down is not an Action, I know not what is; ſo that
inſtead of Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ng from this Text
that the Eunuch was Dipped, they have, I am ſure, Plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37142:44"/>themſelves deep enough into an Ocean of Nonſenſe, which perhaps
may do them more harm (if they have not a care of themſelves) than ever the
Eunuch's going down is like to do them good. But now if we take this Text in
its Genuine Senſe; it ſeems to be this, That they both went down into the
VVater, to the end that <hi>Philip</hi> might Baptize the Eunuch, but in what
manner this Scripture is ſilent; but it ſeems moſt likely by throwing
ſome Water upon him, as we do on thoſe whom we Baptize: And now I leave it
to my Reader to judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this Text (they have ſo gloried in) will
ſo infallibly prove Dipping; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whether it will not infallibly prove
the contrary: But if this is not ſufficient to prove it, perhaps ſome other
may; and therefore I come to conſider of the next, that ſo all their
Miniſters may be heard ſpeak before their Cauſe is loſt.</p>
            <p>Another Text, much urged, to prove a Neceſſity of Dipping, is
<hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16. <hi>And Jeſus, when he was Baptized, went up
ſtraightway out of the Water;</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:37142:44"/>and ſo conclude, that
becauſe he went up, therefore he had been wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water. But ſure I
am, if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Words, we ſhall ſee but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, if any Cauſe,
to ſuppoſe, that in that coming up, it was a riſing from under Water in
Baptiſm; for 'tis ſaid he went up, was ſtill active. 'Tis not ſaid he
was taken up; and I have ſhewn you the Perſon is Paſſive in Baptiſm;
and further, 'tis obſervable, 'tis ſaid he went up when he was Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized:
His going up was an After-Act; now the Anabaptiſt cannot deny but the coming
up out of the Water, as well as going down into it, is a Part of Baptiſm; for
in that Text they ſo urge; where it is ſaid, We are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him in
Baptiſm. Then he mentions Chriſt's riſing again: If then his going up was
after Baptiſm, (as ſaith the Text) then it can never prove a Neceſſity
for us to go down in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm; it ſeems clear to me, that this going up was
not a riſing up from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Water, but a going up from the Water, after
he had been Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; for we cannot ſuppoſe he could<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37142:45"/>live always there; but how he was Baptized before he came up, we know
not; if it was by Dipping, this Text will not prove it, no, not by
Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. The laſt Text I ſhall menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is <hi>John</hi> 3.23.
<hi>And</hi> John <hi>alſo was Baptizing in</hi> Enon, <hi>for there was much
Water there;</hi> and conclude, becauſe there was much Water, therefore they
were Dipped; but ſtill I find my Friends, the Anabaptiſts, harping on the
ſame String, (tho' exceedingly out of Tune) as if they were reſolved to
build their Faith on bare Conſequences; a pretty Inference, <hi>there was
much Water,</hi> therefore they were dipped; what may not a Man conclude at
this rate? Even what he will, from what he will; as if it was not poſſible
for to Dip our Hand where there is much Water, unleſs we tumble in over Head
and Ears. If I cannot come where much Water is, unleſs I am dipped, I ſhall
be more aware of it for the time to come; may not a Man as well conclude,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaw one lighting of a Candle at a good Fire, therefore he is
undoubtedly burnt to Aſhes? I think he may as well<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37142:45"/>ſo
conclude, and better, ſince it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Fire was hot enough to burn
the one, if he went into it; but it may on good ground be queſtion'd, whether
that Water was deep enough to dip the other, had he gone into that. For tho'
'tis ſaid there was much Water there, yet it is moſt certain, that Water
which was counted much with them, would be counted but little with us; for 'tis
reported by ſuch as give us the beſt Account of thoſe Countries, that
Water is ſo ſcarce in thoſe Parts, that a Man may go Seven Days Journey
ſometimes before he finds Water enough to drink; and therefore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to
a Miracle, thoſe Inhabitants are able to live with little or no Drink: And
ſure I am, our late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on this Subject have given good ground to
believe, that Water was not ſo much as the Anabaptiſts ſuppoſe it to
be. But if it was Deep enough to Dip, yet here is no mention made, that they
were ſo; and our Enquiry is not, whether they might poſſibly have been
Dipped, but whether they were ſo; and therefore till this or 
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37142:46"/>ſome other Scripture ſpeaks more plainly of this
Matter, I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Anabaptiſts to be ſilent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it. All
that this Text proves, is, that much Water was there, but how much they made
uſe of in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, it mentions nothing of that.</p>
            <p>And now I have conſider'd ſuch Texts as ſeem to make for
Dipping, I deſire my Reader to conſider well of two Texts that ſeem to
make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, that ſo we may ſee how far the Scripture doth prove an
ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Neceſſity for Dipping in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm: One is, <hi>Acts</hi>
16.33. <hi>And he took them the ſame Hour of the Night,</hi> (that is, <hi>at
Midnight, Ver.</hi> 25.) <hi>and was Baptized, he and all his
ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</hi> For tho' we cannot infallibly conclude they were not
Dipped, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it might be poſſible; yet ſure I am we may as well
conclude from hence they were not Dipped, as they could conclude they were,
becauſe there was much VVater there. 'Tis ſaid, at Midnight, he and all his
were Baptized; now we cannot well<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37142:46"/>ſuppoſe, that they
ſhould riſe, and be plung'd in a River at Midnight. But ſuppoſe they
were willing, yet (ſince Water was ſo ſcarce, as I have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) it may
juſtly be queſtioned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there was VVater enough near at Hand to Dip,
for we cannot ſuppoſe them to go far at Midnight to ſeek for ſuch a
VVater; but there is one Text more, which ſeems as if it were given on
Purpoſe to confute the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Dipping, in <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36.
<hi>See here is Water, what hinders me that I may not be Baptized?</hi>
Obſerve he doth not ſay, here is deep VVater, or much VVater, but only
VVater; ſuppoſing, that if there was but Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, be it more or leſs,
there could be no Hindrance, why he ſhould not be Baptized, on that Account,
as to the Element. Had an Anabaptiſt been there, no doubt but he ſhould
have had a ſharp Rebuke for his Ignorance, thus: VVhat hinders? VVhy, 'tis
not deep enough; but <hi>Philip</hi> never in the leaſt oppoſes him, but
ſeems rather to anſwer by way of Conceſſion, If thou believeſt, thou
may'ſt; as if he<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37142:47"/>had ſaid, True indeed, if there is but
VVater, there can be no Hindrance on that Account. But ſome may ſay, This
was a deep VVater of which he ſpake. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I deſire the
Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts to prove that. But ſuppoſe it was ſo, yet here is no
mention made of that, as not at all material to his preſent Purpoſe. Now
the Eunuch no doubt being inform'd by <hi>Philip,</hi> as well touching the
Manner of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, as the Neceſſity of it, would in all Probability
(had Dipping been the only way) have ſaid, See, here is VVater enough to be
Baptized in; but ſince he only mentions VVater, and <hi>Philip</hi> ſeems
to conſent to him, I frame an Argument thus; If nothing can hinder a Perſon
being Baptized (as to the Element) where there is Water, then Dipping is not
abſolutely neceſſary; but nothing can hinder where there is Water,
therefore Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping is not abſolutely neceſſary; the major is moſt
evident, for there may be Water where there is not enough to Dip any one in.
The minor is clear from expreſs Scripture; See here is <pb n="83" facs="tcp:37142:47"/>Water, what hinders? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Clearly holding forth, that the
not being deep enough to Dip in, could not hinder; for tho' it is by way of
Interrogation, yet it carries in it the Force of an Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. So that tho'
we ſee from hence ſome Water is neceſſary, yet this Scripture gives us
not the leaſt Countenance to believe, or think, that much Water is
neceſſary; but doth in Words next to moſt expreſs Terms prove the
contrary unto us.</p>
            <p>Thus, I hope, I have not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Scripture, that ſome
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants have a Right to Baptiſm, but alſo have given good Proof, that our
Way of Baptizing, by throwing or pouring Water upon the Face, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to
the Mind of God; or at leaſt have given as good Proof for that, as can be
given for Dipping, and better; and ſince the Scripture doth as well approve
(to ſay no more) of our Way of Baptizing as of Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, doth not the Law of
God and Nature direct and excite us to uſe that Way, which may be leaſt
hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37142:48"/>to our Bodies? For if God give us but equal Liberty
to Baptize, by Dipping, or ſome other more ſafe Way, we ought to avoid
Dipping, (eſpecially in our cold Climate) ſince we cannot Dip in the Winter
Seaſon, eſpecially without endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Lives; ſo that of
Neceſſity the Ordinance muſt ſometimes be long deferred, and I am
ſure we have no Preſident for that. <hi>Lydia</hi> and her Houſhold, the
Jaylor and all his, were immediately Baptized, when thoſe two believed; but
now if we were to imitate them (and ſhould Baptize, by Dipping) we muſt
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly hazard the Lives, even of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult in the Winter; and whether of
theſe three we ſhould chuſe, to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptize by throwing Water on the Face,
ſince the Word of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves that Way as well as any other, or Dip them in
the Winter Seaſon, (when we have no expreſs Precept, or Preſident in
Scripture ſo to do) and ſo endanger the Life, or ſinfully to deferr the
Ordinance, I leave it to you to judge; by long deferring the<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37142:48"/>Ordinance, we certainly Sin, by Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or Plunging the Party under
Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, may, under ſome Circumſtances, be in Danger to commit Sin (to ſay
no more) but to Baptize, by pouring on of Water, carries no Appearance of Evil
in it.</p>
            <p>I have heretofore, for ſome time, preached occaſionally in
<hi>Burnham,</hi> in the Hundreds of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> where there were many
Anabaptiſts, (tho' at great Variance among themſelves, one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty moſt
vehemently accuſing another, becauſe one Party Baptized any that were
Adult, if they deſired it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were Believers or not; by reaſon
of which, they, in a ſmall Village, ſet up Meeting againſt Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
whereby I ſee they are fallible in ſome things, and ſo may be in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)
and there I was informed by one that well knew it, that ſome Women being
perſwaded to be Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped ſoon after Childbearing, were immediately taken
ill, and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:37142:49"/>I hope I have ſaid enough as to the manner
how this Ordinance may and ought, under our Circumſtances, to be
adminiſtred, and now deſire my Chriſtian Friends, the Anabaptiſts, to
prove, that the Word is never uſed to any other End, than to ſignifie
Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or Plunging the whole Body under Water; or becauſe they went down
into the Water, or were where much VVater was, that therefore of Neceſſity
they muſt be dipped; but if none of theſe can be proved, (as I am moſt
certain they cannot) I hope they will no more contend about this Point, but
will ſee it their Duty to comply with us in our way of Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, ſince
they cannot thus hazard their Lives, by Dipping, without tempting of God;
ſince we may as lawfully uſe ſome other way, leſs dangerous to the
Body. But if I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail in this, (yet ſince we have ſo much to
ſay, in Vindication of our Practice) I hope they will ſuſpend their
Uncharitable Cenſures, which I find them ſo prone unto; may I judge 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37142:49"/>of ſome Mens Spirits by their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; the Poyſon of
Aſps ſeems to be under their Tongue. 'Tis not long ſince I ſaw a Book
put out by one of the moſt eminent of the Anabaptiſts; who writing
againſt one of ours, who for Piety, Gravity, and Miniſterial Ability,
deſerved to be more Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably treated by him, (however in that Point
differing from him); and in that he charges his Antagoniſt with Railery and
Unbecoming Language, telling him how unlike ſuch a Spirit is to do good in
Controverted Points; and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes by the Grace of God to diſcover no
ſuch Spirit in his Writing againſt him. But this Gentleman had either a Bad
Head, or a Malicious Revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Heart, for within a few Pages, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of
Confuſing him, (which he hath diſcovered himſelf in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of
moſt to be unable to do) he falls into ſuch Scurrilous, Filthy, Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
Language, as for modeſty ſake I omit, rendring much more of that Nature
than ever he had received. From whence I have cauſe to fear that Gentleman
was not much influenced by<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37142:50"/>the Grace of God, while he no
ſooner ſcarce reſolves, by God's Grace, againſt a known Sin, which he
pretends to abhor, but commits it again and again deliberately, and ſeemingly
with the greateſt delight; and rather than conceal his Wit in making a
Jeſt, will commit a Sin to the Diſhonour of God, and Wrong of his own Soul.
It would have been well for that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man if he had never Promiſed by God's
Grace, unleſs he had had more Grace to perform his Promiſe; while he, like
that Diſobedient Son, ſaid, I go, but went not; it will be well for him, if
ſuch as are no more eſteemed by him than Publicans, do not get into the
Kingdom of God before him. I hope my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting doth not in the leaſt ſavour
of ſuch a Spirit, and therefore deſire my Friends, the Anabaptiſts,
impartially to weigh what I have laid down; and if it will not hold weight in
the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuary, reject it; if it doth, let it not be rejected
becauſe of the weakneſs or unworthineſs of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument; but rather
let it be received becauſe it is the Mind of God. If you<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37142:50"/>receive Light into any Truth herein, bleſs God for it: But if
through my weakneſs I have laid down any thing Erroneous, then I deſire
that in as mild a Spirit they confute me with ſolid Arguments from Scripture;
which Confutation ſhall not break my Head, or inrage my Heart, nor I hope,
cauſe me to ſpeak unadviſedly with my Tongue, but ſhall be as a
precious Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to me. I long to ſee more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Truth
(acknowledging I know but in part, and ſo can but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy in part); and if
God will make uſe of an Anabaptiſt to inform me, to the end I may know the
Ways and Truths of God more perfectly, I hope I ſhall rejoice. I muſt
confeſs, in the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome Authors of the Anabaptiſt
Perſwaſion, I have been ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convinced that I am in an
Error, that I am the more confirmed in my preſent Sentiments, while I find
that in their Endeavours to confute us, they wreſt the Scripture, and moſt
groſly abuſe Authors they cite for them. Sometime ſince I read an Author
on this Subject, ſuppoſed to be Mr.<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37142:51"/>
               <hi>Danvers,</hi>
whom upon Examination I find dexterous at abuſing Authors, as if he was
reſolved to confirm his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion from Antiquity, <hi>per fas aut nefas,</hi>
right or wrong; he there cites <hi>Calvin</hi> againſt Infant-Baptiſm, (I
had almoſt ſaid <hi>Calvin</hi> againſt himſelf) on his Expoſition on
<hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. thus, That Men may rightly offer themſelves in Baptiſm;
Confeſſion of Sins is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, otherwiſe the whole Action would be
nothing elſe but ſport: But leaves out his words immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
(no doubt on purpoſe, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe his Cauſe had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed,
and his abuſe of that worthy Author diſcovered) his Words are theſe,
<hi>Porro notandum eſt de Adultis hic verba fieri;</hi> that is, Let it be
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I am ſpeaking here concerning Adult: And who differs from him in
this? Not I. But as to Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, I could weary my reader to cite
paſſages to that purpoſe; eſpecially out of his common places; but his
Judgment is ſo well known, I may ſpare my Labour: Had this Author had as
much Honeſty as Learning, I<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37142:51"/>am perſwaded he would have
cited the whole paſſage of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s. If no Body could have read
<hi>Calvin</hi> in Latin, how miſerably would this Author have beguiled his
Ignorant Reader. The ſame Author hath filled his Book al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt with
citations of Authors; but if he hath dealt no better with them, than he did
with <hi>Calvin,</hi> (as 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain he did not with ſome of them) no
wonder he concealed his Name, leſt on this account it ſhould be rendred
hateful to the World. Why did he not cite that whole paſſage of
<hi>Calvin</hi>'s? May not Scripture it ſelf be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Blaſphemy at
this rate? I do aſſure my Brethren, the Anabaptiſts, ſuch Men as
theſe will never ſtrengthen their Cauſe were it never ſo good. 'Tis a
poor ſhelter to make Lies our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and under Falſhood to hide our
ſelves; and no commendable practice to force Men to ſpeak in Vindication of
that when Dead, which they abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, wrote againſt, and always ſpoke
againſt while Living.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:37142:52"/>And therefore I would deſire my Friends, the
Anabaptiſts, that if they will again Write in Vindication of their
Sentiments, that they would not always imploy the moſt Learned, but the
moſt Gracious; and that they would fix on a Man of Good Report, a Man Fearing
God, and Hating Wickedneſs; not a Slanderer, or a Reviler, but on ſuch a
one who La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to keep a Conſcience void of Offence towards God and Man;
for though for my own part I am perſwaded many of the Anabaptiſt
Perſwaſion are Perſons dear to God, (I mean of thoſe that are againſt
the Doctrine of Free-Will) and that what ſome of them hold is out of
Tenderneſs of Conſcience; yet that wicked Spirit which hath diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
it ſelf in ſome of their Writers, hath cauſed the reſt to be the
worſe thought of, while in their Writings they ſeem liker unto Men acted by
their own Spirit ſtriving for a Party, than contending for Truth by the
Spirit of God, I would in all Love to my Friends, the Anabaptiſts, caution
them in one<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37142:52"/>thing, and that is, to beware of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting too
much Conſidence in their own Writers, eſpecially in citing old Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors;
for they oft cite this and the other of the Fathers, ſpeaking for Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever's
Baptiſm, and by this Means beguile their unwary Reader, with a ſtrong
Opinion, that they were againſt Infant Baptiſm; (one Inſtance of which I
have cited out of Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> to prove this) as if he that was for
Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptizing Believers, who never were Baptized before, (which is as many of them
do certainly mean) muſt needs be againſt Infant Baptiſm; which is as
unnatural a Conſequence, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, if a Man loves his Wife, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he muſt hate his Child; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as his Love to his Wife is no Hindrance to his
loving his Child. For my part I am for Infant Baptiſm; but withal, I am as
much for the Baptiſm of grown Believers, if never Baptized before. So that
theſe two do no ways contradict each other; I leave this as a Caution for my
Friends for the time to come. I ſhall haſten to a Cloſe, and ſum up all
in a Word of Exhortation to my <pb n="94" facs="tcp:37142:53"/>Chriſtian Friends, the
Anabaptiſts; that if they ſee any weight in what I have ſaid, or cannot
from Scripture confute me; that then they would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace this Doctrine, and
practice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; for 'tis dangerous living in Neglect of that which God
in his Word reveals to be a Duty, as is clear from <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24. There
you read how God ſought to ſlay <hi>Moſes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had but
neglected to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe his Child, longer than the time appointed. Tho'
<hi>Moſes</hi> was dear to God; tho' the meekeſt Man on Earth; tho'
intimately acquainted with God; yet he had died, if his Son had not been
Circumciſed; and what ground we have to think that God will more approve of
our Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Baptiſm as to the Subject now, than he did the Neglect of
Circumciſion, as to the time then, I ſee not; for as God appoints no
Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in vain, ſo he cannot bear to ſee them neglected or
deſpiſed, tho' by his own People.</p>
            <p>And ſure I am, ſuch Parents not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offend God by ſo
doing, but ſeem<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37142:53"/>to be without all natural Affection to
their Seed. <hi>Even the Sea-Monſters will draw out the Breaſt to their
young ones,</hi> Lam. 4.3. And they ſeem Monſters of Parents, that can deny
ſuch a Priviledge to their own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſo rob them of their
Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. Such may fitly be compared to the Oſtridge, a filly Creature,
<hi>Job</hi> 39.16. who is ſaid to be hardned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her young Ones, as
if they were none of hers. Suppoſe a wicked Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent have godly Children grown
up, and ſhould confine them from the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God's Houſe, (tho' he
could not deſtroy their Souls thereby, yet becauſe he did what he could in
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto) any godly Perſon would judge ſuch a one an unmerciful
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; how much more may believing Parents be ſo counted, while they deny
the Infant Seed the Ordinance of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, which God hath given them a Right
unto, tho' they cannot deſtroy their Souls. So that as you would not be
charged for not having natural Affection, as you would not contract Guilt upon
your Souls, and pluck down<pb n="96" facs="tcp:37142:54"/>Judgments upon your ſelves, by
not walking in all the Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs, bring your Infant
Seed to be Baptized, be found in God's Way, doing for them what you can, and
then you may with the more Comfort ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect God ſhould do for them that which
you cannot; and that while you lay them at the Pool ſide, the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may be
made healing to their diſeaſed Souls; for we can never, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Preſumption, expect the Bleſſing of God, in Neglect or Contempt of
thoſe Means he hath appointed, in order to enjoy it.</p>
            <p>Were your Children ſick Corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Nature would ſtir you up
to uſe the Means which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in order to their Recovery; and if
you believe your Infant Seed ſtand in need of Mercy, one would think Grace
ſhould excite you to uſe the Means which God hath appointed for the Good of
their Souls, that ſo they may not curſe you in Hell, for not doing what you
might do, and ought to have done, in order to the bringing them to Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:37142:54"/>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But againſt the Practice of
this Duty I have heard ſome argue thus: Tho' they cannot anſwer the
Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments brought to prove it a Duty, yet they cannot ſee into it; and
becauſe whatever is not of Faith is Sin, hence conclude it would be Sin in
them ſo to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Suppoſe it is ſo, I would ask ſuch whether
it may not be a far greater Sin, that it is not of Faith? Or do you think that
your Sins of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (when Light ſhines ſo clear) muſt not be
accounted for? <hi>Paul</hi> hath declared, that once he was ſo ignorant,
that he <hi>verily thought he ought to do many things contrary unto the Name of
Jeſus;</hi> as in <hi>Acts</hi> 26.9. And he did ſo, and made Havock of the
Church, and Blaſphemed. And here we will ſuppoſe it would have been his
Sin, not ſo to have done, becauſe he verily thought he ought; and ſo, had
it been abſolutely a Duty, he would have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected it. But I would ask
ſuch Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors, if they think it was not his<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37142:55"/>Sin, that he
was ſo perſwaded? Nay, was it not a far greater Sin than we can once
ſuppoſe it to have been, had he in that Caſe acted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Faith
or Perſwaſion? If you deny it, you are guilty of as great Blaſphemy as
ever he was. Well then, it ſeems there is Danger of Sin on either Hand; thou
may'ſt (we will ſuppoſe) ſin in doing it, and thou may'ſt ſin
alſo in not doing it. Now in this Caſe there is a Rule for ever carefully
to be obſerved, That when two Evils lye before us, and one of them cannot
poſſibly be avoided, the leaſt is to be choſen; and if this Rule is to
be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, then to me it ſeems far ſafeſt for ſuch to Baptize
their Infant Seed, ſince their doing that which they are not fully
ſatisfied in, may be but acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally a Sin, but their not doing that which
God hath made known to be a Duty, (whether they, thro' Ignorance, ſee it to
be ſo or no) is directly a Sin; and more eſpecially is it ſafeſt for
ſuch as are Members in ſuch Churches, where the Paſtor and Majority of
the Church are of that Judgment, becauſe<pb n="99" facs="tcp:37142:55"/>then by not doing
it, they not only are in Danger (to ſay no more) of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Guilt to
their Souls, by not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found in their Duty, but hereby take the ready way
to cauſe Strife and Contention in that Church, whoſe Peace they are obliged
to ſeek, if our Perſwaſion touching the Lawfulneſs of a thing will make
it Lawful; then this is to meaſure our ſelves by our ſelves, and to
eſteem our own Fancies above the Word of God. Since let the Word of God hold
forth what it will, it no ways obliges (in thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's Judgment)
unleſs I am perſwaded 'tis a Truth. Curſed Doctrine! What is this but
grand Quakeriſm, to preferr the Light within before the Word of God in the
Scripture? <hi>But if</hi> (as Chriſt ſaith) <hi>the Light within be
Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> (as ſure it is when it oppoſes the written Word) <hi>then
how great is that Darkneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, Chriſtian Reader, I have in all Plainneſs of Speech
taken Liberty freely to expreſs my Sentiments about the Doctrine of Infant
Baptiſm; and<pb n="100" facs="tcp:37142:56"/>whatever the Effects may be, if I know my
Heart, I deſigned nothing in it but God's Glory, and thy Good, and to put an
end to our unprofitable Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences; and ſhould I miſs my Aim in this
latter Reſpect, yet I hope this will not indirectly cauſe our Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
to be wider; for what if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fully agree in this, yet ſince we agree
many of us in Fundamentals, and hold one Lord, and one Faith, this
Conſideration ſhould ſurely more unite us, than our Differences in
ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Matters ſhould divide us; we cannot ſuppoſe, while ſo much
Darkneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains upon our Underſtandings, that we ſhould all be fully of
one Mind in all things, any more than we can ſuppoſe we ſhould all be of
the ſame Complexion, or Stature of Body; but as it is enough, in order to
bring us into a rational Converſe, that we are all Men and Women, tho' we may
vaſtly differ in Features, and Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Body; ſo it ſhould be
enough to reconcile us in Love and Affection, that we are Chriſtians, tho'
not in all things of the ſame Mind, and ſame<pb n="101" facs="tcp:37142:56"/>Judgment,
and that we are all Fellow-Travellers to the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi> Tho' we
may not walk in the ſame Path, or tread exactly in each others Steps, ſure
I am, when we get to Heaven, we ſhall ſweetly agree. O deſirable Day!
when <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſhall no more envy <hi>Judah,</hi> nor <hi>Judah</hi>
vex <hi>Ephraim;</hi> when we who now know but in part, and ſee but darkly,
ſhall then ſee Face to Face, and know even as we now are known; when all
our dark and confuſed Conceptions about the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpel
ſhall all vaniſh and diſappear, as the Miſts and Fogs before the
riſing Sun. And when that time (much of which was ſpent in Striving and
Contending) ſhall whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſpent in Praiſing and Admiring him that
loved us, and waſhed away our Sins in his own Blood; how ſhall we then all
be imployed (who are Saints) in the ſame Work, ſing all the ſame Song,
all joined in the ſame Aſſembly, all behold and love the ſame Object?
Yea, how ſhall we then hugg and embrace each other, as Fellow-Heirs of the
ſame Kingdom,<pb n="102" facs="tcp:37142:57"/>and Children of the ſame Father, and
Members of the ſame Body. I am fully ſatisfied our Differences are not ſo
great here, as our Love to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be there; we ſhall no more
ſtrive about the Way, when we enjoy the End.</p>
            <p>And ſince we are ſo unlike fully to agree here, and ſo
certain to agree there, how ſhould it make all the ſincere Lovers of Peace
(who have been mourning for theſe Diviſions which are among the People of
God) cry out with the moſt Earneſt and Longing Deſires, come Lord
Jeſus, come quickly? <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:57"/>
            <head>A QUESTION Briefly Handled, CONCERNING <hi>What State or
Condition the Soul is in, in the very Act of Coming unto Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:58"/>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:37142:58"/>
            <head>A QUESTION Briefly Handled, CONCERNING <hi>What State or
Condition the Soul is in, in the very Act of Coming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>READER, we live in a Luxurious Wanton Age, when many, even of
Profeſſors, who inſtead of <hi>Offering Violence to the Kingdom of
Heaven,</hi> inſtead of <hi>giving all Diligence to make<pb n="106" facs="tcp:37142:59"/>their Calling and Election ſure; who inſtead of earneſtly
contending for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> are ſpending
moſt of their Precious Time no better than thoſe <hi>Athenians, Acts</hi>
17.21. either to tell or to hear ſome new Thing. To mention all thoſe new
Opinions which have been vented of late by Men of Corrupt Minds, <hi>Reprobate
concerning the Truth,</hi> would be tedious to me to Write, and unprofitable to
you to Read. I ſhall only Diſcourſe Briefly upon one, which is this, That
Sinners wreeking in their Luſts, muſt come to Chriſt as they are. 'Tis
too well known how this Notion hath been ſpread abroad of late, and received
too even with ſuch full ſatisfaction and content, that it is a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel
Truth, that by ſuch all others are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed as no Goſpel Preachers,
that dare open their Mouths to oppoſe it: And ſure I am, when Error thus
abounds, it highly concerns ſuch as are ſet for the Defence of the Truth,
to open their Mouths in Vindication of it. I confeſs I have a long time only
bewailed theſe things, to ſee the Truths of the Goſpel 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37142:59"/>Deſpiſed, and Precious Souls lye Entangled in the
Snare of the Devil, and unwilling to be delivered; <hi>But while I refrained my
Speech the Fire kindled;</hi> and now of neceſſity I muſt ſpeak in
Defence of the Truth as it is in Jeſus, come on what will; and I do it for
theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe I have been judged Erroneous by ſome
(who have been too empty of Knowledge, or full of Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice) who have heard me
oppoſe this Doctrine, who I have reaſon to think are no leſs concerned
than thoſe <hi>Epheſians, Acts</hi> 19.34. who without conſulting the
Truths the Apoſtle had Preached, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lawfulneſs of their
Idolatrous Practice, cry out like Mad-Men for the ſpace of two Hours,
<hi>Great is</hi> Diana <hi>of the</hi> Epheſians; and no wonder, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they Lived upon the Silver Shrines; and had their Goddeſs been contemned,
their Craft had been ended. And ſince I have delivered my Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on this
Point, it ſtands me in hand to Vindicate it, ſince I have Truth on my
ſide; for otherwiſe I<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37142:60"/>ſhould rather take ſhame to
my ſelf: And ſince it muſt needs be difficult for any, or at leaſt for
moſt to judge of ſuch deep Myſteries and Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceties upon a Tranſcient
hearing, I am willing to expoſe my Sentiments, that ſo I may either
ſilence my Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, or they may ſhame me. For my part, as I never
durſt utter any thing raſhly in ſo weighty a Point, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had exactly
weighed it in the Ballance of the Sanctuary; ſo I am ſo far from recanting
any thing I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered on this Point, (notwithſtanding all the Calumnies
of my Adverſaries, whoſe Eyes the God of this World hath in part blinded)
that I hope I ſhall be able to defend it to my laſt Breath; and I am the
more encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to defend this Truth, That no Man can or ought to come to
Chriſt in his Sins, by the good Succeſs I have had in many private
Conferences about it; for I never yet Converſed with any that oppoſed it,
but either I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced them of their Error, and brought them to embrace
the truth they<pb n="109" facs="tcp:37142:60"/>once deſpiſed, or at leaſt ſo
ſtopped their Mouths that they have been able no longer to be Gainſayers;
and indeed what can be ſaid againſt the Truth? That will ſtand, when
Errors will, like the Chaff, be driven away: Errors are but Windy
Doctrines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second</hi> Reaſon moving me to clear this Point, is,
becauſe 'tis ſo weighty a Doctrine, and even the turning Point of
Chriſtianity, the Foundation Stone of all the Building; and Errors in the
Foundation are dangerous; what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concern than to know how a Soul muſt
cloſe with Chriſt? Since that Soul that cloſes not with him, ſhall
never be Saved by him: <hi>For he that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not ſhall be Damned,</hi>
Mark 16.16. And how unmerciful muſt that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter be to Souls, and
unfaithful to Chriſt, that canſt ſee a Multitude at once running on with
ſuch a Lie in their Right Hand, and not inform them. If we ſee one going to
Drink down ſome Deadly Poiſon, though the Perſon through a Diſtempered
Brain, or by violence of ſome ſtrong Temptation<pb n="110" facs="tcp:37142:61"/>deſire to Drink it; yet if we know it, and do not our utmoſt to
prevent it, we cannot be clear of his Blood; ſo when we ſee Perſons
imbibing Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Doctrines, we ought ſpeedily to provide an Antidote, and
that though we cannot inform all in all the deep Myſteries of the Goſpel,
by reaſon of that groſs Darkneſs that hath covered many; yet that we
might not ſhun to declare the whole Counſel of God, whether they will hear,
or whether they will forbear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third</hi> Reaſon, Becauſe the Error I oppoſe, not only
paſſes for a Truth with many, but for ſuch a Truth as doth moſt
magnifie the Grace of God, and ſo is like to do the more harm. When Error
appears with a bare face, it will ſeem ſo Deformed, that but few will fall
in Love with it; but when the Devil wraps himſelf in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s
Mantle, it's hard toknow him. This Doctrine ſets up Free-Will by Craft, and
that under a Notion of Free-Grace; and though nothing differs more than thoſe
Two yet the Patrons are minded to let the World ſee what they can do by 
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:37142:61"/>Art; and whether they cannot make ſome take bitter for
ſweet, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 5.20. But becauſe that Monſter of Free-Will is but
of low eſteem with ſome, therefore for love they have to this Creature,
they have beſtowed a new Garb upon it, and have changed its Name too; calling
that which always went by the Name of Free-Will, now Free-Grace; whereby they
have ſo altered the Property of the thing, that the owners thereof ſcarce
know it; and ſo Gild over their Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Pill that it may go down the
bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth,</hi> Becauſe this Doctrine I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſuiting
ſo with our Corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is like to infect the more: But I ſhall not
ſtay you any longer at the Threſhold, but lead you into the Point before
us. But that our Differences may not ſeem greater than they really are, I
ſhall lay down ſome things, as Cautious to prevent miſtakes; for I am
perſwaded that moſt of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Differences do ariſe from a want of a
right Underſtanding of each<pb n="112" facs="tcp:37142:62"/>others Terms; and therefore
obſerve carefully.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Enquiry is not concerning the State and Condition
which Chriſt finds the Soul in, when he firſt comes to take hold on us by
his Spirit, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Regenerating of us; if it was, I would readily grant,
he then finds the Soul wreeking in Sin indeed, without the leaſt propenſity
or inclination to do Good; yea, to every Good Word and Work Reprobate, with a
ſtrong incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to Evil, in a Dead, Blind, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, Senſeleſs, and
Stupid Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the Snere of the Devil: In this State we all are by
Nature, and conſequently in this State he muſt find all when he comes to
Change their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, our Natures being all the ſame, as derived from one
Common Root; though our Actions may differ accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the various
Temptations we may meet with. But 'tis about the Souls coming to Chriſt;
between which a clear diſtinction muſt be made; for though Chriſt enable
us to come to him, or believe in him, yet he doth<pb n="113" facs="tcp:37142:62"/>not
Believe for us to excuſe us: The Act of coming is ours, and till the Soul
thus come the union is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat; I grant when Chriſt comes thus to the
Soul, that Soul ſhall come to Chriſt; yet his coming to us, is not our
coming to him, though the Cauſe of our coming: Things that are
inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, muſt not be confounded; the Humane and Divine Nature are
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable in Chriſt; yet the Divine is not the Humane, nor the Humane
the Divine: So in Marriage, the Man conſents to the Woman, and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to
the Man; but yet the conſent of the Woman is not the conſent of the Man. So
in this Caſe, Chriſt is firſt willing, and he makes us willing, yet his
Will and our Will are diſtinct.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor are we Enquiring by what Power the Soul is enabled to
come to Chriſt; for tho' I have juſt cauſe to queſtion, whether thoſe
that differ from me in the other, will agree with me in this; yet for my own
part, tho' I plead for a mighty Change wrought in order to our coming to
Chriſt, yet<pb n="114" facs="tcp:37142:63"/>I freely acknowledge this Change to be of
God; and that the very Seeds of our Life of Sanctification are from Chriſt
working as a moſt free Agent in us, and that it is a mighty and
irreſiſtible Power by which he works.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Nor are we Enquiring what Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue there is in this Act of
coming in order to our Juſtification or Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For though I believe,
and the Scripture affirms, that unleſs we Believe, we ſhall never be
Juſtified nor Glorified, yet I believe both are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Riches of
God's Free-Grace: It is Free-Grace that works this Change, enabling of us to
come; and it is Free-Grace that we are accepted when we do come.</p>
            <p>But poſitively the Enquiry is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is ſuch a thing
as a Change wrought in the Soul, in order to our coming to Chriſt? Or whether
we muſt come as we are, in a Natural and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate State, wreeking in the
Filth of Sin, and Power, and Dominion of<pb n="115" facs="tcp:37142:63"/>our Luſts? Or
whether the Drunkard, Swearer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> can or ought, without any
Change, to come in thoſe Luſts to Chriſt? So that the Queſtion is,
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Sinner can or ought to come to Chriſt in his Sins? But before I
affirm or deny, I muſt further explain, if poſſible, what we mean by
coming, and what by coming in our Sins, leſt my Oppoſers, when not able to
ſtand their Ground, ſhould ſlip out at ſome Back-door. Now, by coming
to Chriſt, I underſtand belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Chriſt according to Scripture
Dialect, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. and to put all out of
doubt, I have been aſſured again and again from the Mouths of thoſe that
differ from me in this Point, that they mean nothing elſe; and by coming in
Sin, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, for one utterly devoid of any Principle of Grace, one
in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and Bonds of Iniquity, and not one that only falls
into Sin: And ſo I have alſo been aſſured by my Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers they mean;
and indeed we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand it otherwiſe; for tho' the beſt of
Saints have Sin, yet the leaſt of Saints is not a Sinner. I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh 
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:37142:64"/>between Actions and a State, a Sinner in this Senſe is
not oppoſed to Perfection, but to Sincerity: So that in the moſt plain
Terms, the Queſtion lyes thus, Whether a Perſon utterly devoid of all
Grace, and under the Power and Dominion of Sin, can or ought to believe in
Chriſt in that State, before any Change be wrought in him? This ſome
affirm, and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: And in ſpeaking to this Point, I ſhall prove none can
come thus in their Sins to Chriſt; and then, that none ought to come thus in
his Sins to Chriſt. I prove the former from moſt expreſs Scripture,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19. <hi>And what is the exceeding greatneſs of his power to
us-ward who Believe;</hi> and if we cannot believe without this Power, then not
as we are; for all are not acted by this Power, <hi>John</hi> 6.44. <hi>No man
can come unto me, except the Father which hath ſent me draw him.</hi> Now I
would ask if all Men are thus drawn? If not, you give away the Cauſe; if you
ſay they are, then it follows that all muſt actually be Saved, or elſe
ſome are able to reſiſt thoſe drawings;<pb n="117" facs="tcp:37142:64"/>the latter
of which is Grand Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, the former many degrees worſe. So
<hi>John</hi> 15.5. <hi>For without me ye can do nothing.</hi> Now I would ask,
if coming to Chriſt is not ſomething? Nay, is it not the moſt noble act
the Soul can put forth; and that which is moſt pleaſing and acceptable to
God? And if ſo, the Text ſays, without Chriſt we cannot do it. Now I
would ask, if every Man hath Chriſt in him, as the Quakers affirm? If you
ſay he hath, you ſhew what you are; if not, then when aſſiſted by
Chriſt we do not come as we were. Thus you ſee how expreſly the Scripture
is on my ſide; and whether we may moſt ſafely truſt that Word of God,
or the Deluded Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Men, judge ye.</p>
            <p>And as I have proved it from moſt expreſs Scripture; ſo I
ſhall further prove it from thoſe Metaphors the Scripture uſes to
expreſs it: As firſt, It is frequently ſtiled a Coming; a Metaphor or
borrowed Expreſſion from a Man walking from one place to another. And from
this two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations<pb n="118" facs="tcp:37142:65"/>offer themſelves for the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming and illuſtrating the Truth, I have affirmed; for as no Man can
act corporally till he is firſt alive; ſo no Man can put forth ſuch a
vital Act as believing in Chriſt, till Chriſt hath firſt infuſed into
him a vital Principle; and till then, a Dead Man may as well walk, as a Man
Spiritually Dead come to Chriſt. Now then I ask, have all Men ſuch a vital
Principle? If you affirm it, you oppoſe the Scripture, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1.
if you deny it, then you either give me the Cauſe, or affirm a Dead Man can
walk: And further, in all Corporal Motion, there is the Term, from which and to
which; ſo in the Spiritual Motion of the Soul to Chriſt, we come from Sin
to Chriſt. And now I have proved this from Scripture, I ſhall cite ſome
Authors of my Judgment, that ſo my Reader may ſee it is not only my
Opinion: And I ſhall only cite ſuch as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of this Opinion ſeem
to admire as well as I, that ſo you may ſee how they not only oppoſe the
Scripture and me, but alſo thoſe Authors which they<pb n="119" facs="tcp:37142:65"/>ſeem to confide in more than either, that ſo you may ſee how
theſe, like Mad-Men, even tear themſelves. The Learned <hi>Pemble</hi> is
of my Mind in his Treatiſe of Grace and Faith; and there ſpends many Pages
to prove that the habits of all Grace are infuſed into the Soul in
Regeneration, before an Act of Faith can be put forth by that Soul; and why
theſe Men ſhould not as well believe him in this, as well as in his Notion
of Eternal Juſtification (eſpecially ſince he hath clear Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on
his ſide for the former, but not a word for the latter;) ſeems ſtrange to
me: But indeed I need not wonder, ſince they that thus pick and cull this
Author, taking what ſuits with their Opinion, and rejecting the reſt, do
ſerve the unerring Word of God no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And if they dare ſerve
<hi>Paul</hi> ſo, 'tis no wonder if they deal ſo with <hi>Pemble.</hi> Dr.
<hi>Goodwin</hi> is on my ſide; in his Treatiſe on the
<hi>Epheſians,</hi> he hath theſe words, <hi>'Tis affirmed,</hi> ſaith
he, <hi>by Sound and Able Divines, and that on good Ground, that the Principles
of all Grace are infuſed into the Soul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<pb n="120" facs="tcp:37142:66"/>the Soul
can put forth an Act of Faith;</hi> with ſeveral paſſages to the ſame
purpoſe, which for brevity ſake I omit. Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> gives abundant
Teſtimony to the ſame Truth; in his Treatiſe on Juſtification he
ſaith thus, <hi>Juſtifying Faith is not to be found in any but thoſe
whoſe Natures are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and in whom there is a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of all
Grace.</hi> Thus you may ſee in a little how far theſe Divines were from
this Error. But becauſe I have not to do with profeſſed Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but
with ſuch as privily bring in this Erroneous Doctrine, I ſhall therefore
come to conſider what their Pleas are, and in Anſwering of them I ſhall
further clear the Point I am up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and then I ſhall anſwer ſome
Queſtions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some I have heard ſay by coming in Sin, we mean ſuch
muſt be ſenſible of Sin, and ſo come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If ſuch mean as they ſay, why do they not
always explain their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? And ſure I am, if this is all ſuch 
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:37142:66"/>mean, ſuch Preachers are miſerably miſtaken by their
Hearers, who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon conclude they muſt come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Change. 'Tis well
known how, with ſome, Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion; and I am well
ſatisfied this is but a Jeſuitical Shift, that when they cannot juſtifie
that rotten Notion of coming to Chriſt in their Sin, then they tell us (if we
will believe them) they mean only ſenſible of Sin; but this Notion ſhall
never be heard of till no other Anſwer will ſerve: But what
Soul-couſening is it to ſay one thing and mean another; ſuppoſe they do
mean ſo, Pulpits ſhould be places to to Explain things in. But that this
Cobweb may not cover ſuch Deceit, conſider when they ſay, we muſt be
ſenſible of Sin; they mean, either that they have ſome Sin adhering to
them, or elſe that they are ſenſible they are in that Moment in a Sinful
Unchanged State: If they mean the former only, they give away the Cauſe; for
we are enquiring into the State; and certainly if not in a Sinful State, 'tis
becauſe in a Changed State, unleſs ſome do not<pb n="122" facs="tcp:37142:67"/>come
into the World in ſuch a State, and ſo need no Change; but if by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſenſible of their Sin, they mean a Sinful State; then they are ſenſible
of that which is, or is not; if ſenſible of that which is, then they openly
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſuch are in an Unchanged State, only add a Sence to the thing it
ſelf; if they ſay they are ſenſible of a ſinful State, when their
State is not ſo; then this is no leſs than to affirm that a Deluſion is
the only Qualification prerequiſite in order to our coming to Chriſt:</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſome may ſay, we own 'tis Chriſt that brings
us, and ſo we do not rob Chriſt of his Honour, or Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate any thing to
our ſelves as you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but we affirm he brings us unto himſelf in
our Sins. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, 'tis not enough to honour Chriſt, to ſay he
doth a thing, unleſs the thing done be well done; 'tis far from being an
Honour to Chriſt to make him the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Sin: But to come to a more
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Anſwer, I lay down this Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That ſome things are
impoſſible<pb n="123" facs="tcp:37142:67"/>to be done by God himſelf; the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
affirms 'tis impoſſible to God to Lie, and that he cannot deny himſelf;
whatever is ſinful cannot be done by that God that is Goodneſs it ſelf;
nor doth this inability ariſe from weakneſs, but ſtrength. Some things
are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Nature, and ſo cannot be done, as to make it Dark and Light
at the ſame time, and in the ſame place; to make a Man Dead and Alive at
the ſame time, and in the ſame reſpect. Now I ſhall enquire whether
'tis not impoſſible, under one or both of theſe Conſiderations, for a
Soul to be brought to Chriſt (though by the power of Chriſt) in his Sins as
aforeſaid: I ſhall not now inſiſt on the former, how far ſuch a Work
would ſavour of Sin; but ſure I am in the latter Sence it is
impoſſible; and for the clearing this, Conſider, our coming to Chriſt
is an Act of the Will; we are willing to renounce all confidence in the
Fleſh, and to rely alone on Chriſt. Now I would ask whether this Will is in
all Men by Nature; if ſuch deny it, then where this Will is, there is a
change<pb n="124" facs="tcp:37142:68"/>wrought in that Soul, and a great change too,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. <hi>A willing People in the Day,</hi> &amp;c. If ſuch
ſay this Will is in Men by Nature, then they not only prove themſelves
<hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> but virtually deny what before they affirmed, that they
come by the power of Chriſt: But if they ſay, tho' unwilling by Nature, yet
they are made willing by the Power of Chriſt to come, yet without a Change in
the Will, this is a grand contradiction in Nature to ſay, that a Perſon who
is unwilling, ſhould be made willing, and yet no change made in his Will; and
yet this groſs abſurdity my Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers will unavoidably hereby pluck down
upon their own Heads; I think it is ſafeſt to attribute the Work to
Chriſt in ſuch a manner as may not in the leaſt ſavour of Sin, or carry
in it the leaſt abſurdity or contradiction. But now Chriſt can no ways be
chargeable with Sin in bringing a Soul from Sin; nor is it the leaſt
contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſay a Man of unwilling is now changed and made willing; or
for a Dead Man, when made alive, to act and<pb n="125" facs="tcp:37142:68"/>move; it would
have been ſtrange to ſee <hi>Lazarus</hi> have riſen and walked while
Dead; but not ſtrange at all to ſee him walk when Chriſt had quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened
him: So in this caſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But ſay ſome, when we preſs Sinners to come to
Chriſt in their Sins, we do not mean that they can ſo come, but that they
ought ſo to come: And foraſmuch as this Reply hath the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſhew of
truth; I ſhall conſider what of truth it really hath in it: Now to this I
anſwer, by making this neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſtinction, 'tis one thing for it to
be the Duty of Sinners to come to Chriſt, another thing to come in their Sins
to Chriſt: And though I readily grant 'tis the Duty of ſuch as are in their
Sins to come, that is, to ceaſe to do Evil, and to learn to do Well; and by
the ſtrength of God's Grace to leave the Sins they now are in, yet I
abſolutely deny 'tis their Duty to come in their Sins. Though I do not expect
all ſhould reach this, who are not uſed to diſtinctions. I ſhall
endeavour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to illuſtrate this to you thus;<pb n="126" facs="tcp:37142:69"/>tis
one thing for it to be the Duty of an unchanged Perſon to come, another for
that Perſon to come unchanged. 'Tis the Duty of Sinners to keep the Law, but
not to keep it in their Sins: 'Tis the Duty of a Man Drunk to praiſe God,
becauſe he is not in Hell, but 'tis not his Duty to praiſe him Drunk: His
praiſing denotes the Work, his praiſing of him Drunk would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the
manner how he ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Work, and if this ſhould be granted, it
would as much be ſuch a Perſon's Duty to be Drunk, when en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in that
Work, as to be engaged in that Work.</p>
            <p>To illuſtrate this, God hath made it our Duty to Praiſe him,
and to Worſhip him in Spirit and Truth; the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip denotes the Work, to
do it in Spirit is the manner of Working, and one is a Duty as well as the
other; ſo that tho' it is the Duty of a carnal Man to Worſhip God, yet not
to Worſhip him carnally. So though it is the Duty of Sinners to come, yet not
to come in their Sins; for this would make Sin a Duty; there may be a 
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:37142:69"/>great difference in Sence, when there may be but little in
Sound. To give you an Inſtance, whole Chriſt is one thing, the whole of
Chriſt is another thing; the Proteſtants own whole Chriſt to be
every-where; but Hundreds have choſe rather to burn at a Stake than to own
the whole of Chriſt to be every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: But I ſuppoſe the Patrons of this
Opinion will never ſuffer much for Truths no clearer diſtinguiſhed than
thus; though to any underſtanding Perſon the difference is exceeding great;
but unleſs a Man can find ſome Mens Underſtandings as well as Truths, the
Truths they prepare and explain to them will be but asſom any Pearls caſt
before Swine, which will rather En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them, make them turn again and rend
them, than be profitable unto them: So Chriſt aſſumed the Nature that was
Polluted, but not the Pollution of that Nature.</p>
            <p>But to put all out of doubt, I ſhall come in a more familiar
Stile to prove, that though it is undoubtedly the Duty of Sinners to come to
Chriſt, or believe<pb n="126" facs="tcp:37142:70"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:37142:70"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:37142:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:37142:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:37142:72"/>in Chriſt; yet it is not ſo much as their Duty to come
in their Sins to Chriſt; the great difference between which, I hope by what
hath been ſaid you now will underſtand: For as I have hinted, when I ſay
'tis the Duty of a Sinner to come, it denotes no more than thus, that it is his
Duty to come from Sin to Chriſt; but for any to come in their Sins to
Chriſt, denotes they muſt bring their Sins to Chriſt; which is as
impoſſible as to bring the Eaſt and Weſt into one Point; the
diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between Chriſt and Sin not being ſo little as many do
imagine, <hi>What Communion hath Light with Darkneſs?</hi> Chriſt is well
pleaſed to ſee a Soul come from Sin; but it is impoſſible for a Soul to
come in Sin, nor is it his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo to come; which I prove from theſe
following Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 1. That which no Man was ever able to do, is not
ſo much as our Duty to do; but no Man was ever able to come to Chriſt in
his Sins, therefore 'tis not ſo much as our Duty ſo to do. My Major I
conceive will<pb n="129" facs="tcp:37142:72"/>be granted, only carefully obſerve, I ſay
that which no Man ever was able to do; I do not ſay that which no Man is now
able to do, is not his Duty: For if we conſider Man in his fallen State, ſo
many things are his Duty to which he hath no ſtrength to do, and God may
juſtly condemn him for not doing them, becauſe his Inability was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
by himſelf; but God commands us to do nothing now but what <hi>Adam</hi> had
Power to perform, if God had but made it known to be his Duty: And for any to
deny my Major Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, would be to affirm, that God hath given Man a
Law, which was abſolutely impoſſible to be kept, and damns his Creatures
for not obeying of it, which hath too harſh a ſound to be received for a
Truth. Minor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: But no Man ever was able to come to Chriſt in
his Sins. That we who are in a fallen and unregenerate State cannot come to
Chriſt, while ſuch, I hope I have ſufficiently proved; and it is
impoſſible that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have Power to come in Sin before he
had committed Sin. Therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,<pb n="130" facs="tcp:37142:73"/>that tho' it is
the Duty of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to come from Sin to Chriſt, or to believe in Chriſt,
becauſe Thouſands have by Grace been ſo enabled to come, and
<hi>Adam</hi> had once a Power to believe any thing that God ſhould reveal;
yet becauſe never any was able to come to Chriſt in his Sins, therefore
'tis not ſo much as a Duty ſo to do; for tho' God hath ſent many Sinners
to Hell, for not coming to Chriſt, yet I am confident he never ſent one
Soul to Hell for not coming to Chriſt in his Sins; for this would be to damn
Souls for not continuing in Sin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 2. He that ought to come to Chriſt in a
ſinful State, ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in him in the ſame State; but no Man can
continue in Chriſt, and a ſinful State. Therefore no Man ought to come in a
ſinful unrenewed State to Chriſt. The former part of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is clear
from <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. <hi>As ye have therefore received Chriſt Jeſus the
Lord; ſo walk ye in him.</hi> Now you know the preſent Enquiry is, what
State and Condition the Soul is in when by Faith<pb n="131" facs="tcp:37142:73"/>it
receives Chriſt. Say ſome, in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renewed State, without any Principle of
Grace, (miſerably forgetting that this coming is it ſelf a Grace) and under
the Power and Dominion of Sin; then ſaith the Text, <hi>So walk ye in him.
Minor,</hi> but none that receive Chriſt can or ought to continue in Sin, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Therefore if any Man is in Chriſt, he is a new
Creature.</hi> So <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>If Chriſt be in you, the Body is
dead, becauſe of Sin,</hi> &amp;c. So that of neceſſity the Opinion I am
confuting muſt be falſe, or the Word of God not true. But for the more full
Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the weaker ſort, who can eaſier raiſe Objections
againſt the Truth, than underſtand what it is, I ſhall come now to
anſwer ſome Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>Muſt not Sinners be invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to come to
Chriſt? Is not the Goſpel ſent to Sinners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Tho' the Goſpel is ſent to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, yet not
to encourage them in Sin; and tho' Sinners muſt be invited to 
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:37142:74"/>come, which Work of inviting I hope, while I live, I
ſhall be employed in, yet ſure I am, tho' Sinners muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to
come, yet not to come in their Sins, as aforeſaid; and ſuch as do ſo
invite them, I am ſure have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in God's Word ſo to do. I
know a Text, which invites ſuch as <hi>labour, and are heavy laden, to come,
Matth.</hi> 11.28. which certainly implies a Change. I know a Text, that
invites the Thirſty to come, which ſtill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies a Change. I know a Text,
which ſaith, <hi>Waſh ye, make ye clean, come now, Iſa.</hi> 1.17,18.
denoting ſuch a Work muſt be wrought in us before we come, tho' not by our
Power. I know a Text, which ſaith, <hi>Let the Wicked forſake his Way, and
the Unrighteous Man his Thoughts, and let him return,</hi> Iſa. 55.7.
denoting a Neceſſity of a Change in Heart and Life, when we return; but I
know no Text that either invites or commands Sinners to come to Chriſt in
their Sins; and let the Patrons of that Opinion produce but one ſuch Text,
and I ſhall acknowledge my Ignorance, and do promiſe for ever 
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:37142:74"/>to be ſilent, and vindicate this Point no more.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>But muſt not Sinners come to Chriſt as
Sinners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, If by theſe Words, as Sinners, you mean ſuch as
are utterly devoid of any Principle of Grace, (for that is the Enquiry) then I
hope I have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved ſuch cannot ſo come. But if you mean
ſuch as only have the Remainders of Sin in them; ſo ſuch may come, or
none muſt come; but I have ſhown you how the Remainder of Sin in the
Regenerate doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly denominate them Sinners; nor is this any thing to
the Point in Hand, for I am diſcourſing of the Power of Sin in an
unregenerate Soul; he that is Born of God, ſinneth not; that is, not with
Delight and Approbation; therefore it ſavours of moſt groſs Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
thus to ſtile Saints Sinners, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not perfectly free from Sins, when
God himſelf makes ſuch a vaſt Difference between them. So that theſe
things being laid down, my Anſwer is,<pb n="134" facs="tcp:37142:75"/>We are not to come
as Sinners in the Sence aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>But muſt not we bring our Sins, and lay them on
Chriſt? If not, where muſt we lay them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Foraſmuch as this is judged an unanſwerable
Plea by ſome, I ſhall labour the more clearly to anſwer it; and the
rather, becauſe it is ſuch weighty Concern; we all come into the World in
Sin, and have multiplied our Tranſgreſſions, as the Sands, which lye as a
heavy Burden upon us, ready to ſink us into Hell; and it highly concerns us
to know how to have this Burden removed; nor is any thing more dangerous than
to make a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in this Caſe. Now I grant God the Father did once in a
way of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty lay all the Sins of all the Elect on Chriſt, imputing the
Guilt of all thoſe Sins to Chriſt; the Scripture is clear to prove this,
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. <hi>And the Lord hath laid on him the Iniquity of us
all.</hi> He came to finiſh Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and to make an end of Sin; 
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:37142:75"/>He ſtood in our Room and Stead, and bore the Curſe due
to the Elect, that they might not for ever lye under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; and to this
dying Sacrifice we muſt look for Comfort, as appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereto of the
Father, under the Sence of Sin; for without ſhedding of Blood there is no
Remiſſion. This is that Scape Goat that muſt bear our Sins into the
Wilderneſs; nor is there any other Way for our Sins to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. But tho'
God imputed the Guilt of Sin to Chriſt, to the end that he might make
Satisfaction to Juſtice, yet God himſelf did not lay the Filth and Dominion
of Sin upon Chriſt; and that is the Point in Hand. Hence he is ſaid to be
without Spot, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. He was a
Sin-Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed, but not a Sinful Offering. If Chriſt had no Spot, then
no Filth; for that will make Spots where it is, or elſe it would not be
Filth. But tho' God did once lay Sin on Chriſt in the Sence aforeſaid, yet
now 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible Sin ſhould be laid upon him by us; and thoſe who
preſume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſuch a thing, do evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare<pb n="136" facs="tcp:37142:76"/>they look upon him not to have compleated his Work; and tho' the
Scripture affirms, that <hi>by one Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath for ever perfected them
that are ſanctified, Heb.</hi> 10.14. yet thoſe Perſons are for laying
Sin upon him again, (and that in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as God himſelf never did)
and ſo do what in them lyes to crucifie the Lord afreſh, and to put him to
open Shame, and to render all he hath done as imperfect, and ſo virtually
over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the very Foundation of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; ſince if Sin be laid upon
him again, he muſt ſuffer for it again; ſince Sin was never laid upon
Chriſt to any other end than to ſatisfie the Juſtice of God for it; and
as this was the end, ſo either Chriſt hath fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied Juſtice or
not; if he hath, then no more Sin can be laid upon him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he muſt pay
the Debt twice, which is not conſiſtent with Juſtice; but if they ſay
Chriſt hath not, then they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their curſed Hereſie.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe who are ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that their filthy
Luſts muſt of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity<pb n="137" facs="tcp:37142:76"/>lye on Chriſt or them, I
would ask them this Queſtion, where will thoſe Sins lye at Judgment? For
'tis expreſly ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. <hi>He ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the ſecond
time without Sin unto Salvation;</hi> then ſince he will not then bear them,
they are like to return to them again. 'Tis a moſt groſs Miſtake to think
Chriſt cannot come to us, and by his Spirit waſh us in the Laver of
Regeneration; but the Filth which he waſhes off from us muſt defile him; as
if a Phyſician could not cure another, but the Diſeaſe muſt return upon
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Chriſt by his Spirit deſtroys the Power of Sin in us, but we
can in no Propriety of Speech be ſaid to lay our Sins upon him.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there are ſome few Texts which ſeem to ſome to
favour the Point I have been confuting, I ſhall cite them, and ſee how far
they will prove the Point. One is in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.18. <hi>Look ye
blind;</hi> here ſay ſome, ſuch as have no Sight muſt look. To which I
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I own many things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded which we cannot do; but 
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:37142:77"/>this is not the Point; but the Queſtion is, whether
theſe blind ought to look without Eyes? Which to affirm, would be a grand
Contradiction; for if he looks, it muſt be with his Eyes. When God commands
Sinners to look, they muſt look with their Eyes; for as a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Faculty
is neceſſary, in order to our looking, ſo in this Caſe there muſt be
a Power wrought in us by God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are able to look, before we can by
Faith look unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Next Text is <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. there God is ſaid to juſtifie
the Ungodly; from whence ſome argue thus: If in the Act of juſtifying us
God finds us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and yet we are ſaid to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith, then
it ſeems evident the Soul is ungodly when he believes. I am ſatisfied this
Text hath been no little abuſed in our Day, while it hath been molded into
what Form ſome pleaſe to promote their own Intereſt. The Apoſtle tells
us ſome Scriptures are hard to be underſtood, and I am perſwaded this is
one of them; nor do I much wonder if the Ignorant wreſt <pb n="139" facs="tcp:37142:77"/>it; I ſhall labour therefore to clear this ſweet Portion of
Scripture, that ſo you may know the Truth, as it is in Jeſus. Now the great
Enquiry for the clearing this Text, is to know what we are to underſtand by
the Word Ungodly; and I ſhall ſhew you, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Negatively, How
we are not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it; and, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Poſitively, How we
muſt underſtand it. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively; By ungodly we are not to
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand one utterly devoid of all Grace; and this will abundantly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
both from the Context and Text it ſelf; you will find in the foregoing
Verſes this Inſtance is taken from <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> from whence it is
evident, and I think paſt all Diſpute, that if by Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly we are to
underſtand ſuch as have no Grace, then it will follow, that
<hi>Abraham</hi> had then no Grace; but that cannot be ſuppoſed, for
<hi>Abraham</hi> had then been a Believer many Years, and yet is ſaid to
believe in him that juſtifieth the Ungodly. And this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears further, even
from the Text it ſelf; for here is believing ſet before Ungodly; ſo that
this Ungodly Perſon<pb n="140" facs="tcp:37142:78"/>muſt be one that hath Faith, and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, not one without Grace; for Faith is it ſelf a Grace; ſo
that this Text is ſo far from proving Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before, or without
Faith, that it ſtrongly proves the contrary; becauſe this ungodly Perſon
is before ſtiled a Believer; and ſuch as lay ſo much Streſs on the
Order of the Words, as to conclude, that becauſe the Word Juſtifie is ſet
before Ungodly, that therefore the Perſon Juſtified muſt be an unrenewed
Man, would do well to conſider here is Believing ſet before the Word
Juſtifieth. But to ſhew you in the next Place,</p>
            <p>Poſitively, By Ungodly I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand one that is Legally ſo;
one that hath not any Righteouſneſs inherent in him to anſwer the Demands
of the Law; and thus a Perſon is renewed Ungodly: For ſince the Law
requireth perfect and perpetual Obedience, hence we who are now renewed, having
been heretofore unrenewed, and now in part defiled, hence 'tis impoſſible,
but that we muſt in a Legal Sence be Ungodly.<pb n="141" facs="tcp:37142:78"/>This Text
ſtrongly proves, that the Grace of God in us is not that for which we are
juſtified: Therefore to me it ſeems a groſs Miſtake to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, as
ſome do, that God accepteth of our ſincere Obedience in the room of
<hi>Adam</hi>'s perfect Obedience; for this is to ſet up our ſelves
inſtead of Chriſt. God will not juſtifie any but upon perfect Obedience;
either inherent in us, or imputed to us; not in us, for you ſee the Law
pronounces Believers ungodly Men; ſo that of Neceſſity we muſt look
beyond our Grace, for that is imperfect, even to that compleat and ſpotleſs
Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; nor am I fingular in my Sence of this Text, for
I have the Reverend and Learned Doctor <hi>Goodwin</hi> on my ſide, in his
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on part of the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> Part I. Page 389. ſaith
he, <hi>The meaning is not one that hath no Grace, for then</hi> Abraham
<hi>ſhould not have been ſaved:</hi> He inſtanceth in him; and adds,
<hi>To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on him that juſtifieth the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theſe are the Terms on
which he muſt believe. Firſt,</hi> Theſe are the Terms on which he muſt
believe all<pb n="142" facs="tcp:37142:79"/>his Days; ſo that you ſee the Doctor was
far from underſtanding Ungodly here, for one without Grace, unleſs you can
ſuppoſe a Believer may live all his Days, and have no Grace; and he gives
the Reaſon elſewhere, why ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and have Grace, are termed
Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; becauſe, ſaith he, they are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves legally ſo. Thus
you ſee this Text makes nothing to prove that a Perſon can believe, while
in an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed State, but much to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Thus I have at large cleared
this Scripture, and have anſwered all ſuch Queſtions as I know proper to
the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Point; and doubt not, after all, but this Doctrine of Sinners
coming in their wreeking Luſts to Chriſt, will appear to be erroneous to
all, but ſuch as are under the Power of their Luſts, and no more paſs
current for a Doctrine of Free-Grace, as it hath done; nay, this is ſo far
from being a Doctrine of Free-Grace, that it is grand Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, and a
ſetting up of Free-Will; which will appear to any underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reader, if
we conſider that the Soul in coming to Chriſt, moves from a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious 
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:37142:79"/>Principle, or a Natural Principle; if from a Gracious
Principle, then the; Soul doth not come wreeking in his Sin to Chriſt; for
it's a grand Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſay a Sinner is a Gracious Perſon; but if
they ſay the Soul moves from a Natural Principle, this is a grand Free-Will,
as ever <hi>Arminius</hi> himſelf deliver'd. The Subſtance of this
Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, whether the Union between Chriſt and the Soul begins on
Chriſt's Part or ours? Or whether without any Priority in Nature, the Soul
from a Natural Inclination, and Chriſt, do mutually conſent; they who ſay
the Soul comes in its Sin, make the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to begin on Man's Part; they that
ſay the Soul acts in that Caſe from a renewed Principle, do own the Union
to begin on Chriſt's Part; they that ſay they both conſent together as
aforeſaid, attribute as much to Man as to Chriſt, and by ſo doing,
diſcover themſelves to be no ſincere Friends to the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, but
rather, <hi>Judas</hi>-like, betray Chriſt with a Kiſs; and whether of
theſe doth moſt magnifie the Grace of God, to affirm the Union begins on 
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:37142:80"/>Man's ſide, or that Man Naturally conſents to
Chriſt, at the ſame time with Chriſt; without any Priority in Nature on
Chriſt's ſide; or they who affirm as I do; that our conſent to Chriſt
is the effect of his conſent to us, I muſt leave it to my Reader to
judge.</p>
            <p>Or the Subſtance of this Queſtion is this, whether the Soul is
firſt Active or Paſſive? They that affirm that the Soul comes to Chriſt
in its Sins unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, make the Soul firſt Active; they who ſay the Soul
acts as a renewed Soul, make it firſt Paſſive; which is ſuch an
undoubted Truth, that I dare venture my Salvation on it; and I hope I have
clear Scripture on my ſide, <hi>John</hi> 5.25. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay
unto you, the Hour is coming, and now is, when the Dead ſhall hear the Voice
of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall Live:</hi> Which cannot be meant
only of the Reſurrection of the Body, becauſe it is ſaid the Hour now is;
but it hath reſpect to the quickening of the Soul from the Death in Sin: And 
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:37142:80"/>it clearly proves that Chriſt finds the Soul Dead, when
he comes to put forth this Quickening Voice; for look, as with
<hi>Lazarus,</hi> Chriſt calls him while Dead, Lazarus <hi>come forth;</hi>
and by this Call infuſes Life into him, and ſo enables him to come forth:
Had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther called, he might have waſted his Lungs in calling, before he
would have ſtirred. So Chriſt calls us when Dead in Sin, and with the call
puts Life into us, and ſo enables us to hear and obey his Voice,
<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. <hi>You hath he quickened,</hi> &amp;c. Then it ſeems
Chriſt quickened them; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if he do not, we cannot; and as
<hi>Gahazi</hi> could only lay the Staff on the Face of the Child, but could
not put Life into him till the Prophet came, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.31,32,33. ſo
till Chriſt the great Prophet bring home the Word to the Heart, we call and
cry in vain; we can but Prophecy over dry Bones, but that Breath that quickens
them is from the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.5. Hence Chriſt the Second
<hi>Adam</hi> is called a quickening Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. And to
prove yet further, that<pb n="146" facs="tcp:37142:81"/>the Soul is firſt Paſſive
before it is Active. We have another moſt clear Text, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.
<hi>For we are his Workmanſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c.
Mind, we are crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Now you know that in Creation we were Paſſive, as
the Clay in the Hand of the Potter: Man cannot be ſuppoſed to have any Hand
in Creating of himſelf; ſo that as Man was firſt purely Paſſive in
the Hand of God, and muſt receive a Natural Life, before he could perform a
Natural Action; ſo is the Soul as purely paſſive, while God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes
the firſt Grace whereby the Soul is enabled to put forth that vital Act of
coming to Chriſt; ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.20. <hi>I was found of them that
ſought me not: I was made manifeſt unto them that ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not after
me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot but pity ſuch deluded Souls as receive the Doctrine I
am confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for a Doctrine of Free-Grace, who are ever Learning, and never
able to come to the Knowledge of the Truth. It's a ſore Judgment to be given
over to believe a Lie, and to be left to feed on a Stone inſtead of Bread,
and not<pb n="147" facs="tcp:37142:81"/>to be able to diſcern between a Fiſh to
nouriſh us, and a Scorpion to ſting us. I have obſerved one great
difference in Doctrine among ſome Diſſenters, whereby Meeting is ſet up
againſt Meeting in the ſame Town, to the great diſhonour of God, and
hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to Religion lyes in this. Some affirm what I have proved, and are
therefore termed Dark, Legal, Muddy Preachers; the others look upon
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be the only Goſpel Preachers, becauſe they cry down all
Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Soul when it comes to Chriſt, Gracious ones not
excepted: But who will be beſt able to defend their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine at the Great
Day, I hope, by what hath been ſpoken, you will be able to Judge, if they
mean what they ſay, or indeed know what they ſay. The difference between us
is this, they own Chriſt to be the Purchaſer of all our Benefits, ſo do
I; but here we differ, they ſay we muſt go to him in all our Sins for them;
I ſay, he that purchaſed them, doth enable us to come to him, and ſo I
attribute the Application to him alſo; and now<pb n="148" facs="tcp:37142:82"/>judge who
Preaches Free Grace moſt clearly; I make Chriſt the <hi>Alpha and Omega,
the Beginning and the End;</hi> they make him only the Beginning; and affirm,
that if Sinners do not come as they are, they muſt be Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. If Chriſt
ſaves none but ſuch as come to him thus in their Sins, that is, by their
own power, (for if Sinners are acted by the Power of God, then they do not come
as they are) what a Remnant will be ſaved? A Remnant did I ſay? Nay, I dare
affirm, if that be true, not one Soul ſhall be ſaved: Man is naturally
unwilling to come to Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 5.40. <hi>And ye will not come to
me that ye might have Life:</hi> Which Text only proves there is a Will in Man
not to come to Chriſt; though it be for Life, they will Die rather; and how
hard a thing do Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters find it to perſwade Souls to come to Chriſt.
Now if this is the Nature of all, then thoſe whoſe Wills are not changed
will never come; and if their Wills are changed by a Divine Power, and they 
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:37142:82"/>ſo enabled to come, then they do not come in their Sins
in an unchanged State; only God can change the Will, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi>
110.3. <hi>They ſhall be a willing People in the Day of thy Power:</hi> How
little is Chriſt beholden to ſuch who would fruſtrate his deſign in
Dying? He expected a Seed for to ſerve him as the effect of his Sufferings:
But at this rate, he muſt have none unleſs they come to him upon the weak
Legs of their own Free-Will. They will give Chriſt the Honour to lay down his
Life for the Sheep, but deny that it is he which goes into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to
ſeek them; or that it is he that brings the Loſt Sheep home upon his
Shoulders. No, ſay they, the loſt Sheep muſt come home of it ſelf or
Periſh; <hi>The Son of Man is come to ſeek and to ſave that which was
loſt, Luke</hi> 19.10. And they who own him to be a Saviour, and deny him to
be a Seeker, do virtually deny him to be a Saviour: For as it is obſerved of
Sheep, when once they ſtray from the Fold, they never return again of
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ſo now we are gone aſtray<pb n="150" facs="tcp:37142:83"/>from God; if
he will Save us, he muſt Seek us; hence <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 2.24. Man is
compared to the Wild Aſs, to denote, I conceive, thus much, that as that
Creature will never come to Hand, till ſuch time as ſhe is in Pain to bring
forth; ſo Man will never return from his Wilderneſs State, till he feel the
Pangs of the New Birth in his Soul.</p>
            <p>Now though I cannot but hope ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that differ from me in this
Point are dear to God, (holding this Notion out of Ignorance or Blind Zeal) and
that they are upon a good Foundation, yet I am verily perſwaded this
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine they defend, will be found in the Great Day to be but as Hay, Wood,
Stubble; or, if poſſible, ſome more Cumbuſtible Matter.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding I have thus clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtated and proved this to
be a Truth from Scripture, that none can or ought to come to Chriſt in their
Sins, yet I doubt not but many who never were led into the Knowledge of their
own<pb n="151" facs="tcp:37142:83"/>Hearts, to ſee their Natural Enmity againſt
Chriſt, and Utter Inability to perform any Duty Spiritually, will be ſo far
from ſetting to their Seal that this is true, that they will be but the more
exaſperated. We read in <hi>Acts</hi> 7.54. that when the Apoſtle had
reproved thoſe Jews for their Sin in Crucifying Chriſt, to the end it might
not be their ruin, <hi>they were cut to the Heart;</hi> but inſtead of
Bleſſing God for ſuch a Faithful Reprover, 'tis ſaid, <hi>they
gnaſhed on him with their Teeth.</hi> Man is Naturally prone to ſet up
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and when he cannot make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Purchaſer of his
Salvation, he would have a Hand in the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and how unwelcome ſhall
a Faithful Miniſter be to ſuch, when they come to beat down their Carnal
Confidence, and to ſpoil their Glorying in the Fleſh? And how hard for a
Miniſter who ſhuns not to declare the whole Counſel of God and whoſe
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is that Chriſt alone may be exalted, to Preach ſuch Doctrine as
this, but by and by ſome will be offended?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:37142:84"/>Such Doctrine as this would not be received
from Chriſt himſelf by ſome, was he now on Earth, <hi>John</hi> 6.65,66.
<hi>And he ſaid, Therefore ſaid I unto you, that no Man can come unto me,
except it were given him of my Father. From that time many of his Diſciples
went back, and walked no more with him.</hi> Mind, no ſooner had he told them
in plain words what I have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, but from that time many went back,
and walked no more with him. Now, if I am judged Erroneous, yet I hope ſuch
as differ from me in this Point will not judge Chriſt ſo; yet why Chriſt
ſhould be judged a true Witneſs, and I a falſe Witneſs, for relating
his very Words, I ſee not; but if I am, yet it more encourages me that
Chriſt is on my ſide, than it ſhall diſcourage me, though all the
Devils in Hell wore againſt me; being fully ſatisfied that he will be the
Judge at the Great Day, not only of our Lives, but of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; nor will
any Doctrines paſs for Truth then, if they have not a Divine Stamp upon them;
and ſure I am, this Doctrine I oppoſe hath none.<pb n="153" facs="tcp:37142:84"/>I am
ſatisfied, if thoſe ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the
<hi>Revelation,</hi> they can find no Text written, to prove that Sinners can
or ought to come to Chriſt in their Sins; though many Texts prove it the Duty
of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to come. But to take a review of the forecited Text, and to ſee
who they were that forſook Chriſt for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering ſuch Doctrine; you may
ſee, Verſe 64. <hi>Such as believed not;</hi> none elſe: Chriſt turns
him to the Twelve, <hi>Will ye alſo go away? Peter,</hi> on the behalf of the
reſt, replies, <hi>Lord, to whom ſhall we go? Thou haſt the Words of
Eternal Life.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Lord, doſt thou think we are ſo
unacquainted with our own Hearts, as to go from thee for delivering that Truth,
that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> who have but taſted thou
art Gracious have experienced? Theſe are the Words of Eternal Life, and
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou mayeſt as well ask us, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are willing to miſs of
Life, as forſake thee for theſe Truths ſake. Thus you ſee, however
contemptible this Doctrine was then to thoſe that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not, or may be to
ſuch whoſe Eyes<pb n="154" facs="tcp:37142:85"/>are not yet opened, or at leaſt, who
ſee no clearer into Divine Myſteries than he who ſaw Men as Trees; yet
this was judged ſuch a Fundamental Truth to the Twelve, that it behoved them,
as they tendred the Salvation of their Souls, to receive it.</p>
            <p>In a word, and I ſhall cloſe. Tho' thoſe that differ from me
in this Point, may for my good-will become my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe I tell them
the Truth; yet in love to their Souls, I would have them conſider, whether
this Doctrine they defend, doth not exclude the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God from having any
hand in the Application of the Benefits purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt to the Soul?
And if it doth, I hope you will ſee it to be an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror indeed. Now I think
none dare deny, but that upon our coming to Chriſt, his Benefits are applied
to all. Now the Queſtion is, how or by what power the Soul is enabled to
come? Say I, as renewed and born of the Spirit, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.3,5. ſay
they, (though without one Syllable in Scripture to prove it) no, the Soul comes
wreeking in all his Sins, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed,<pb n="155" facs="tcp:37142:85"/>unrenewed; and if
ſo, then judge if this is not to exclude the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit wholly from having any
hand in this Work? For if ſuch as come to Chriſt have the Spirit, then they
do not come as they are in their Sins.</p>
            <p>Let me cloſe all with a Word to you my Auditors, and
eſpecially to you my Brethren; I chiefly deſigned what is contained in this
Book for you; that you may be eſtabliſhed in the Truth as it is in Jeſus.
Take you heed of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting Sound Doctrine, leſt God give you over to believe
a Lie. 'Tis the Truth muſt make you free: Stand you therefore and Enquire for
the good Old Way, and walk therein, and you ſhall find reſt to your Souls.
Contend you earneſtly for the Faith once deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Saints. Beware of
ſuch pretended Lights as do not ſhine forth in God's Word. In a word, if I
have delivered nothing in this Book, but what I have proved from Scripture,
then I hope you will ſee it your Duty to receive theſe Truths. 'Tis ſad
when any Love Darkneſs rather than<pb n="156" facs="tcp:37142:86"/>Light. But if any of
you, after all my Labour for your ſakes, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject theſe Truths, I
leave this Book, not as a Legacy, but as a Witneſs againſt you at the Great
Day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37142:86"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
